<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lynn Fisher</title>
    <atom:link href="https://lynnandtonic.com/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Lynn Fisher’s Thoughts on Design and the Web</description>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <link>https://lynnandtonic.com</link>

    <item>
      <title>Sabbaticals and muscle memory</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>On 22 May 2014, I publish a little camera illustration. It’s drawn with CSS and one HTML element (a div).</p><p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/single-div-camera.png" alt="A CSS drawing of a vintage camera."></p><p>With this, my favorite little side project is born.</p><p>I draw some food, a Captain America shield, and an iPhone battery. CSS solidifies itself as my favorite artistic medium.</p><p>With each drawing, I share a tweet. People seem to really dig it. It encourages me to keep going.</p><p>I give the project a name and buy <a href="https://a.singlediv.com">a domain</a>.</p><p>Mozilla Hacks invites me to <a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/2014/09/single-div-drawings-with-css/">write a tutorial</a>.</p><p>My web heroes see the project, share it, and praise it. I can’t believe it. I’m positively glowing 😻.</p><p>A Single Div hits Reddit and Hacker News. It’s exciting and horrible at the same time. It inspires my favorite tagline: I specialize in projects that make people say “I don’t get it.”</p><p>The drawings become more complex as I try out new techniques and find new challenges.</p><p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/web-a-single-div.jpg" alt="A selection of drawings from A Single Div."></p><p>A Single Div is featured in Net Magazine. I’m beside myself with joy.</p><p>People holler at me about SVG. This seems to hold even for my projects that follow. Something <a href="https://a.singlediv.com/#svg">I can joke about</a> fondly now. Yes, I’ve heard of SVG.</p><p>I give a talk on <a href="https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/talk-illustration-with-css/">CSS illustration at CSSDay</a>. I share A Single Div and talk about art with a bunch of developers. I’m holding on to this high.</p><p>A Single Div becomes a project I can work on even when I’m feeling stuck. A few hours here or there and the site continues to grow.</p><p>I learn <em>so much</em> about CSS behavior. I grow a deep, mental reference I can pull from for my job and paid projects. “Real” projects as people often say. But truly, what project isn’t real?</p><p>I test the limits of my creativity. The constraints help me to see things differently. And to see <em>myself</em> differently. “Can I draw this?” feels like “Gosh, I don’t think I can.” But with enough thinking, it shifts to “Holy crap, it works.” Honestly I still look back at some of these drawings and wonder how the heck I did that.</p><p>I’ve learned so much from you, little side project. Happy fifth anniversary (I heard the traditional gift is wood 👇).</p><p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/single-div-five.png" alt="A CSS drawing of the word FIVE made of wood logs."></p><small class="footnote">View this latest drawing and more at <a href="https://a.singlediv.com">a.singlediv.com</a>.</small><p>🍻 Cheers to five more years.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/five-years-of-a-single-div/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/five-years-of-a-single-div/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Sabbaticals and muscle memory</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>In the middle of 2018, I took a 3-month sabbatical from work. It was something I’d been wanting to do for over a year, while I was experiencing pretty severe burnout. I’ve previously shared a bit of <a href="https://vimeo.com/248062321">what that felt like</a>. I was able to stabilize myself for a while with significant help from my personal and professional support system. But extended leave was still calling me.</p><p>There were logistical decisions to be made and questions to answer. How long would I need? What kind of financial place would I need to be in? Would &amp;yet hold my job for me? That all felt easy compared to the more nebulous and philosophical questions on my mind. In hindsight, three months isn’t that long, but our country’s culture has a way of punishing those who step away from work. And it encourages us to punish ourselves.</p><p>I had a lot of thoughts. What if taking time off doesn’t help? What if this time away damages my career in some way? What if I forget things, fall behind?</p><p>What if I lose a part of myself?</p><p>…</p><p>While on sabbatical, I went to my local gym early one morning to shoot hoops. I hadn’t played in years and I knew the court would be empty. Turns out dudes at the gym don’t usually want a 5’3” Asian chick with glasses on their pick-up basketball team. Go figure.</p><p>I used to play every day growing up and played on lots of teams. I was actually pretty good. Maybe on this break I could ease my way back into it.</p><p>As I walked toward the hoop something happened. I dribbled, I squared up, and I took a shot. Swoosh. My arm lingered vertically in the air. Follow through. I grabbed the ball and took more shots. Swoosh. Swoosh. The ball met the wood floor and returned to my hand. Over and over.</p><p>It’s the first time I’ve cried at the gym. Muscle memory is a hell of a thing. All the work and the practice and the connections you made are still there. Even years later, you pick back up and it’s still you.</p><p>I’d just spent a year or so feeling unsure of where I was, feeling unlike myself in ways I couldn’t reconcile. And then that morning, shooting hoops in an empty L.A. Fitness, there I was.</p><p>…</p><p>I didn’t do much web work during my break. I unpacked the pile of moving boxes we’d been living out of, tried <a href="https://twitter.com/lynnandtonic/status/1022871859921006593">making some things out of wood</a>, visited <a href="https://twitter.com/lynnandtonic/status/1018634691732094976">some cool places in Arizona</a>, and watched a good helping of reality television. I was surprised by how much I loved my time away. Maybe I could do this forever.</p><p>And when I returned to work and to the web, there I was, again. Sometimes the work just flows out of you. Intuition is built from years of practice. Habits. Muscle memory.</p><p>A connection between disparate skills zapped into place in my brain. The feeling of effortlessly sinking free throws and the joy of combining CSS properties to make visual magic.</p><p>I’ve read a lot about specialists and generalists. T-shaped people and comb-shaped people. None of these have felt right to me. Every thing I do and learn and try makes this complex web of knowledge and experience. Each new thing strengthens the web and makes it more entangled.</p><p>Maybe I’m a web-shaped person, a web builder. A spider-person. A friendly neighborhood Spider-Woman.</p><p>I’m also sort of the Queen of getting out of shape and then back into shape in a weird wave pattern that never ends. I’ve accepted it and stopped pushing against it. And this I’ve learned, is how I work too. Being constantly prolific isn’t the norm for a lot of creative people. It’s ok to create seasonally. Some seasons we’re hibernating and others the work bursts from our fingertips without hesitation.</p><p>It’s good to rest when we need it.</p><p>If I’m stuck on a problem, I take a shower. Clean my bathroom or take a nap. When I return, the answer is right there clear as day. I joke that procrastination is part of my process, but I do mean it. Sometimes seeing the answers, connecting the dots, takes a bit of time away.</p><p>So if it’s calling you, take a break. When you come back, you’ll be there.</p><p>--</p><p><em>This was originally published on <a href="https://blog.andyet.com/2019/02/06/sabbaticals-and-muscle-memory">blog.andyet.com</a>.</em></p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/sabbaticals-and-muscle-memory/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/sabbaticals-and-muscle-memory/</guid>
    </item>


    <item>
      <title>2018 British Arrows Awards</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>Last month I visited the <a href="https://walkerart.org/">Walker Art Center</a> in Minneapolis where they were showcasing the 2018 British Arrows Awards, celebrating the UK’s most innovative and best moving image advertising.</p><p>The commercials are all impressive, some funny, some deeply moving, and some were basically short films. I love the extra effort that goes into Super Bowl ads here in the U.S. so this was a lot of fun.</p><p>I’ve been thinking about it ever since, so I collected all of the commercials here. They’re worth checking out.</p><p>Here’s what won Commercial of the Year: an ad about normalizing periods. It’s well done!</p><div class="video-container wide"><iframe width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lm8vCCBaeQw" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><p><strong>#Bloodnormal</strong> <br><small>Essity, Libresse/Bodyform for AMVBBDO by Somesuch, directed by Daniel Wolfe</small></p><p>And then the rest. Here’s a YouTube playlist of the commercials that won Bronze, Silver, and Gold (except for the Instagram ad <a href="https://vimeo.com/249225909">A day on planet Stories</a> which you can view on Vimeo). See below for each ad’s individual link and details.</p><p>I think my favorites might be <a href="https://youtu.be/Dw2NOE_6VAU">Viewers</a>, <a href="https://youtu.be/Y_iCIISngdI">What Girls Are Made Of</a>, <a href="https://youtu.be/1MJrRvpjB1I">Differences</a>, <a href="https://youtu.be/IZC02EQqcXc">Timeless</a>, and <a href="https://youtu.be/8SI52fWMp_8">The Gene Project</a>.</p><div class="video-container wide"><iframe width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?list=PLusDsPjWd8nk7SdMXqGF2gIE917xhStSg" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><h2>Bronze</h2><p><a href="https://youtu.be/XW7zZJSGYgU">Best Friends</a> <br><small>Mars Petcare, Dreamies Deli-Catz for adam&eveDDB by Caviar, directed by Keith Schofield</small></p><p><a href="https://vimeo.com/249225909">A day on planet Stories</a> <br><small>Instagram, Instagram Stories for Wieden+Kennedy Amsterdam by Caviar, directed by Dent De Cuir</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/YCoQwZ9BQ9Q">Comic Relief Safety Video</a> <br><small>British Airways, Comic Relief for BBH by 2AM, directed by Becky Martin</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/JuvqaBqUYw0">The Small Prices</a> <br><small>TK Maxx, Spring Summer for Wieden+Kennedy London by Bold, directed by Adam & Dave</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/Dw2NOE_6VAU">Viewers</a> <br><small>Google, YouTube for AMVBBDO by Pulse Films, directed by ThirtyTwo</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/n8aAaGDNosQ">Mo Farah--Smile</a> <br><small>Nike, Nike Running for Wieden+Kennedy London by Rogue, directed by Mark Zibert</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/h3gkLJhFWEA">Rummager</a> <br><small>VISA, Holiday Money for Saatchi & Saatchi by Somesuch, directed by Sam Hibbard</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/F4I5hhEJtp8">Kovonation Street Opening</a> <br><small>CompareTheMarket.com for VCCP Blue by Passion Animation Studios, directed by Dave Scanlon</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/dRzApWZgeCs">Fall Fashion</a> <br><small>H&M for adam&eveDDB by Caviar, directed by Karim Huu Do</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/LzQhHvdDCig">We Are All One</a> <br><small>On, on-running.com for TheBay 13 Institute by Hungry Man, directed by Richard Bullock</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/IgZ-TGTUyf4">E.ON x Gorillaz: A Solar Collaboration</a> <br><small>E.ON, Solar PV Batteries for WCRS by Blinkink at Blink, directed by Noah Harris</small></p><hr><h2>Silver</h2><p><a href="https://youtu.be/mQqJPAx_ARo">It’s perfectly normal. Until it’s kwiffed. Caught Glas</a> <br><small>Kwiff for Droga5 London by Biscuit Filmworks, directed by Jeff Low</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/t_jZd2MUXbc">Women’s Euros 2017</a> <br><small>Channel 4, made by 4creative, directed by Alex Boutell</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/J2uSGFgFn2Q">Barbers</a> <br><small>Apple, iPhone 7 Plus for Apple by Furlined, directed by Dougal Wilson</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/Z9WYkOGYwv0">Snowed In</a> <br><small>Waitrose for adam&eveDDB by Academy Films, directed by Martin De Thurah</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/9zv884-Smrc">Born Confident</a> <br><small>Volkswagen, T-Roc for adam&eveDDB by Somesuch, directed by Nick Gordon</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/o4ewFdCxd5Y">London Needs You Alive</a> <br><small>Mayor of London, Greater London, Knife Crime for AMVBBDO by Academy Films, by Novemba</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/-PgTjhx1VLw">Epic Lift</a> <br><small>MoneySuperMarket, MoneySuperMarket.com for Mother by Blink Productions, The Bobbsey Twins from Homicide</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/nQk98HV8-AA">Anthony Joshua</a> <br><small>Lucozada, Lucozada Sport for Grey London by Smuggler, directed by Christopher Hewitt</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/RL6Wiiq7sg8">I Love Doing Dishes</a> <br><small>Finish, Dishwater Tablets for Wieden+Kennedy London by FRIEND, directed by Ian Pons Jewell</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/Y_iCIISngdI">What Girls Are Made Of</a> <br><small>Nike for Wieden+Kennedy London by Riff Raff, directed by David Wilson</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/M4X4e_truzI">Atlas</a> <br><small>Squarespace, Build A Website for Media Sages by Biscuit Filmworks, directed by Andreas Nilsson</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/pxHpdEHEaV0">Mother and Daughter</a> <br><small>Sky, Sky Cinema for WCRS by StrangeLove, directed by Ben Liam Jones</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/EyijJV_KUN8">It’s perfectly normal. Until it’s kwiffed. Father & Son</a> <br><small>Kwiff for Droga5 London by Biscuit Filmworks, directed by Jeff Low</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/viRSiBCxlS0">140 Years</a> <br><small>Wimbledon for McCann London by Friends Electric and Craft/McCann, directed by Lucas Zanotto</small></p><hr><h2>Gold</h2><p><a href="https://youtu.be/8PstSiTCk74">The Supporting Act</a> <br><small>BBC, BBC One for BBC Creative by Blinkink at Blink, directed by Elliot Dear</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/UWKdI6qMUNM">Clowns</a> <br><small>Audi for BBH by Rattling Stick, directed by Ringan Ledwidge</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/FTaAXPDvnuM">More Than A Game</a> <br><small>EA Sports, FIFA 18 for adam&eveDDB by Smuggler, directed by Adam Berg</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/1MJrRvpjB1I">Differences</a> <br><small>BBC, CBeebies for Karmarama by Smuggler, directed by Joshua Neale</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/xSJQP_klQYY">Delivering Awesome</a> <br><small>Virgin Media, Fibre Broadband for BBH by Rogue, directed by Sam Brown</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/2Ei_XdwSghQ">Fanfare, White Cliffs, Football</a> <br><small>Channel 4, Channel 4 Idents 2017 for 4creative by Blink Productions, directed by Dougal Wilson</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/UcFlyBN7gxM">Boundaries</a> <br><small>Canon, Cameras for VCCP by Riff Raff, directed by Megaforce</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/CkYUVw9wkQ8">Dream Makers</a> <br><small>Honda, FIlm on Four for Wieden+Kennedy London by Time Based Arts, directed by James Allen and Mike Skrgatic</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/OJ7Jsd0yCLQ">The Great British Bake Off</a> <br><small>Channel 4 for 4creative by Blinkink at Blink, directed by Parabella</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/HbzOkNq8aPE">Alive</a> <br><small>Bose, Bose Headphones for Grey London by Smuggler, directed by Miles Jay</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/6FKNyhwUBY4">The Faith of a Few</a> <br><small>Mini, John Cooper Works for Jung von Matt by ANORAK x Somesuch, directed by Daniel Wolfe</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/4uCeeVl_He4">Pride and Breadjudice</a> <br><small>Warburtons, Seeded Batch for SCRS by Another Film Company, directed by Declan Lowney</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/aFHvWMzG6gE">The Button</a> <br><small>Volkswagen, Golf GTE for adam&eveDDB by Independent Films, directed by Gary Freedman</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/IZC02EQqcXc">Timeless</a> <br><small>Lacoste for BETC Paris by Academy Films and Wanda, directed by Seb Edwards</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/bAdpodJkB9c">The Heist No One Is Talking About</a> <br><small>Oxfam for Don’t Panic by Stink Films, directed by Tom Green<br></small>* Disturbing content warning for this one</p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/SvjT38dsxtU">Youth Can Do It</a> <br><small>Prince’s Trust for The&Partnership London by Park Pictures, directed by Andrea Arnold</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/vEEVu4w5LTE">Ostrich</a> <br><small>Samsung, Samsung Gear VR for Leo Burnett Chicago by MJZ London, directed by Matthijs van Heijningen</small></p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/8SI52fWMp_8">The Gene Project</a> <br><small>Unilever, Marmite for adam&eveDDB by Outsider, directed by James Rouse</small></p><hr><h2>Commercial of the Year</h2><p><a href="https://youtu.be/lm8vCCBaeQw">#Bloodnormal</a> <br><small>Essity, Libresse/Bodyform for AMVBBDO by Somesuch, directed by Daniel Wolfe</small></p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/2018-british-arrows-awards/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/2018-british-arrows-awards/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Case Study: lynnandtonic.com 2018 refresh</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>It’s that time of year again where I refresh my portfolio site. The 2017 redesign got a huge response, probably my favorite version of the site ever. If you’re curious, you can <a href="/archive/2017">view the archived 2017 site</a> or <a href="/thoughts/entries/case-study-2017-refresh/">read the case study</a>.</p><p>In sum though, the 2017 redesign featured <a href="https://twitter.com/DannPetty/status/943621861740630017">20 media queries where the site changed drastically every 100px</a>. I knew this year I wanted to build upon that concept.</p><p>In the previous version, the 21 separate layouts each utilized their available space, but their order in sequence wasn’t all that deliberate. I thought it might be interesting if things still changed as you scaled the browser, but the change was <em>meaningful</em> depending on whether you were scaling up or down.</p><p>A few ideas seemed promising: </p><ul><li>Maybe the viewport could zoom in or out on an aerial map or scene. Go from a macro view of something small and zoom out into space.</li><li>Maybe the user could feel like they were moving deeper into a physical space using layered imagery. Like walking through rooms in a first-person video game.</li><li>Maybe things could be “tipped off a table” as the browser edge came into contact or grow in number as the browser grows.</li></ul><p>With all of these, it felt like animation was going to be an important part. I researched and thought a lot about various animation techniques and styles. Should it be CSS-drawn? Should JavaScript lend a hand here? How can I have interesting imagery that changes over many breakpoints without having a massive amount to download? I knew it’d probably be a lot of work, but <em>how much</em> work?</p><p>A good compromise I landed on was animating a single character. I could keep the illustration style pretty simple and possibly show various frames by shifting a <code>background-image</code> sprite in the same way we do for other imagery on our websites.</p><p>So what could be fun with that constraint? I thought about a person moving across the screen as the browser moved or getting more cramped inside a “box” as the browser shrunk. I knew I wanted the animation to work both ways—so you could resize the browser randomly and everything still made sense.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/lynnandtonic-2018-smoosh.jpg" alt="Exploratory illustrations of Lynn’s face smooshed against an implied glass wall."><small class="footnote">some early exploratory sketches</small><p>If anything was going to shrink/grow with the browser, why not clothes? They could shrink teeny tiny and grow huge and baggy. That might be fun. I tried a few illustration styles (including a nod to <em>The Loud House</em>) before settling on paying tribute to the genius <em>Bob’s Burgers</em>.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/lynnandtonic-2018-illo-styles.jpg" alt="Exploratory illustrations of Lynn in different styles."><small class="footnote">more exploratory sketches</small><p>With this style (from the show outro), I could keep things simple and make a fun background that wouldn’t distract from the character animation in the foreground.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/bobs-burgers-credits.gif" alt="An animated gif of Jimmy Pesto Jr. dancing in the Bob’s Burgers outro."><h2>Preparing the artwork</h2><p>I started by drawing three full frames to see if it felt like a good direction to go. All the people I showed laughed when they saw it, so I decided to go all in.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/lynnandtonic-2018-three-frames.jpg" alt="Three illustrations of Lynn, one with tiny, shrunken clothes, one normal, and one with huge, oversized clothes."><p>As I drew all the in-between frames, I realized it would be a lot to download, especially if I was using SVG (so many anchor points). So I continued making every frame for the items that needed it and reusable frames for other pieces.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/lynnandtonic-2018-clothes-sprite.jpg" alt="An image sprite of all the frames for Lynn’s clothing."><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/lynnandtonic-2018-faces.jpg" alt=""><p>The hair, faces, mouths, arms and legs became little reusable libraries. I sprited together as much as made sense to reduce the number of files.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/lynnandtonic-2018-other-sprite.jpg" alt=""><p>And with SVG, every anchor point matters, so I spent some time simplifying and optimizing the artwork in Illustrator. I made small changes to reduce points, like smoothing lines, removing some shadowing, and ditching the ribbed lines on the hoodie’s cuffs.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/lynnandtonic-2018-hoodies.jpg" alt=""><p>I’ll tell you what, I learned a lot of new shortcuts in Illustrator. Nothing quite like extremely tedious tasks to get you streamlining. After export, I ran it through a handful of SVG optimizers until I got a result I felt comfortable with.</p><p>In between all of that, I did dabble with the idea of using PNGs instead. File size was sometimes smaller, but I lost the scaling flexibility I ultimately decided I wanted.</p><h2>Markup and Styling</h2><p>Sorry this isn’t a single div 😂. I set up the background and character with the following markup:</p><pre><code>  &lt;div class=&quot;lynns-burgers&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;lynn&quot;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;other legs&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;other shoes&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;clothes pants&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;other arm arm-left&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;other arm arm-right&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;other hair&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;other shirt&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;clothes hoodie&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;other face&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class=&quot;other mouth&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>
<p>With regards to the CSS, I’ll start by saying I would not have attempted this without a preprocessor. I’m using Stylus variables and mixins a whole bunch to make everything more manageable (I ultimately needed to write over 220 media queries). This does add a lot of moving pieces and a few layers of abstraction. It made it worlds easier for me to accomplish what I needed but, as I’ve realized trying to write this, it makes things a lot harder to explain.</p><p>So, in the interest of time and all of our brain goo, I’ll go over a couple specific pieces that went into producing the animated sequence. If you want to dig in and see all the weird decisions I made, you can <a href="https://github.com/lynnandtonic/lynnandtonic.com">view the source code on GitHub</a>.</p><p>For most of the pieces (like the shoes, legs, clothing, hair), I give the <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> dimensions, declare a background sprite, and position it appropriately. Then its <code>background-position</code> is shifted, giving each media query a new frame of the sequence.</p><img class="wide border" src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/lynnandtonic-2018-placement-other.jpg"><p>Let’s say the frames changed every 20px, and the width of each <code>.hair</code> frame is 100px, then the CSS might look something like this:</p><pre><code>  @media screen and (min-width: 501px) and (max-width: 520px) {
    .hair {
      background-position: 0 0;
    }
  }
  @media screen and (min-width: 521px) and (max-width: 540px) {
    .hair {
      background-position: -100px 0;
    }
  }
  @media screen and (min-width: 541px) and (max-width: 560px) {
    .hair {
      background-position: -300px 0;
    }
  }
</code></pre>
<p>Some of the pieces (like arms, mouths, and chin dimples), needed to have their <code>background-position</code> changed with each query, but also to be positioned and sometimes rotated.</p><img class="wide border" src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/lynnandtonic-2018-placement-arms.jpg"><p>So a media query for these pieces might look more like this:</p><pre><code>  @media screen and (min-width: 501px) and (max-width: 520px) {
    .arm-left {
      background-position: -50px 0;
      left: 103px;
      top: 56px;
      transform: rotate(14deg);
    }
  }
</code></pre>
<p>This is <em>a lot</em> of CSS to write (44 frames for most character pieces), so Stylus is a huge help here. This might need some closer inspection at the source files to really grok, but here’s a preview of what I was doing.</p><p>I was able to reuse a lot of the media query syntax with variables and mixins:</p><pre><code class="language-css">  /* Set min-width and frame increment */
  $min-w = 412px
  $step = 23

  /* Shift background-position only */
  frame(number, args) {
    @media screen and (min-width: $min-w + $step * number) and (max-width: $min-w + $step * (number + 1) - 1) {
      background-position: args;
    }
  }

  /* Shift position only */
  move(number, left, bottom) {
    @media screen and (min-width: $min-w + $step * number) and (max-width: $min-w + $step * (number + 1) - 1) {
      left: left;
      bottom: bottom;
    }
  }

  /* Shift background-position, position, and rotate */
  place(number, args, left, top, deg) {
    @media screen and (min-width: $min-w + $step * number) and (max-width: $min-w + $step * (number + 1) - 1) {
      background-position: args;
      left: left;
      top: top;
      transform: rotate(deg);
    }
  }
</code></pre>
<p>With a bunch of other <a href="https://github.com/lynnandtonic/lynnandtonic.com/blob/master/_styl/pages/home/_variables.styl">variable declarations</a>, I was able to write each of the frames/queries like this:</p><pre><code class="language-css">  .hair
    frame(0, $hair-2)
    frame(1, $hair-3)
    frame(2, $hair-4)
    frame(3, $hair-2)
    frame(4, $hair-5)
    ...

  .arm-left
    place(0, $arm-3, calc(var(--arm-base) * .74), calc(var(--arm-base) * 1.18), 14deg)
    place(1, $arm-5, calc(var(--arm-base) * .72), calc(var(--arm-base) * 1.18), 10deg)
    place(2, $arm-7, calc(var(--arm-base) * .78), calc(var(--arm-base) * 1.22),  9deg)
    place(3, $arm-5, calc(var(--arm-base) * .78), calc(var(--arm-base) * 1.18),  4deg)
    place(4, $arm-5, calc(var(--arm-base) * .76), calc(var(--arm-base) * 1.18),  7deg)
    ...
</code></pre>
<p>I know that <code>place</code> declaration looks a bit scary, but it provided the most clarity for me about what was happening with each query. I’m using <code>calc()</code> and CSS custom properties here which I’ll get to in a bit.</p><h2>Hold up</h2><p>You might be wondering why I didn’t save the entire character for each frame so I’d only have to shift one large image sprite. Why the pain of all these different variables, mixins, and things?</p><p>The practical reason is the sprite would have been a ginormous file, even as a PNG and <em>especially</em> as an SVG. Breaking the illustration into pieces made file sizes more manageable.</p><p>But to be honest, shifting one large sprite just isn’t as fun?</p><p>I wanted to try this and see if I could do it. It was challenging and satisfying figuring out how to organize things, how to piece everything together, and how to work through all the small tweaks to make the animation work. Something something <a href="https://frankchimero.com/blog/2011/the-long-hard-stupid-way/">Frank Chimero, the long, hard, stupid way</a> something something.</p><h2>So what else was involved?</h2><p>There are a few more <a href="https://github.com/lynnandtonic/lynnandtonic.com/blob/master/_styl/pages/home/_breakpoints.styl">media query mixins</a> I used for more fine-grain control of what was happening. A ‘range’ query to have a frame show for multiple <code>$step</code> increments, a ‘hide’ query to add <code>display: none</code> to elements when they weren’t needed (like the legs once the pants grew long), and a ‘last’ query with no <code>max-width</code> for the final frame. Those would show up like this:</p><pre><code class="language-css">  .legs
    ...
    frame(        7,     $legs-1)
    frame-range(  8, 12, $legs-5)
    frame-range( 12, 16, $legs-2)
    hide-min(    16)

  .hair
    ...
    frame(       39,     $hair-2)
    frame-range( 40, 42, $hair-3)
    frame(       42,     $hair-2)
    frame-last(  43,     $hair-14)
</code></pre>
<p>There’s two different <code>$step</code> increments being set: 23px for laptop screens and 47px for monitor-sized screens. Most desktop users should get the full sequence without having to move to a larger screen.</p><p>For tall screens, the artwork gets resized which allowed me to dabble with CSS custom properties. With <code>calc()</code> and custom properties, it was easy to swap in new values depending on the user’s context. I know a transform probably would have worked too, but again, not as fun.</p><p>The site also takes advantage of some PostCSS plugins. I have four CSS files compiling from Stylus:</p><pre><code>  📂 css
    📄 generated-home-base.css    /* base styles */
    📄 generated-home-large.css   /* for monitor views, 47px step increment */
    📄 generated-home-small.css   /* for laptop views, 23px step increment */
    📄 generated-post.css         /* for PostCSS processing */
</code></pre>
<p>Note: If it was possible to use a combination of <code>calc()</code> and custom properties <em>inside</em> the media queries, I could have eliminated the need for separate large.css and small.css files.</p><p>PostCSS plugin <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/css-mqpacker">css_mqpacker</a> takes the large.css and small.css and consolidates repeated media queries. So the many, many media queries would go from something like this:</p><pre><code>  @media screen and (min-width: 401px) {
    .hair {
      background-position: -100px 0;
    }
  }
  @media screen and (min-width: 401px) {
    .legs {
      background-position: -200px -150px;
    }
  }
</code></pre>
<p>to something like this:</p><pre><code>  @media screen and (min-width: 401px) {
    .hair {
      background-position: -100px 0;
    }
    .legs {
      background-position: -200px -150px;
    }
  }
</code></pre>
<p>Seems small, but saves <em>a lot</em> of characters across 220 media queries.</p><p>Then <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/postcss-import">postcss_import</a> compiles the four files into one glorious home.css.</p><h2>Any weird hiccups?</h2><p>I originally had the <code>.lynns-burgers</code> container centered using flexbox. Easy peasy. But when I resized the browser, the artwork would shift left/right slightly every few pixels as it was repositioned. This created a vibrating effect that I did not like one bit.</p><p>Using the ol’ fixed position, then translate pattern did the trick. I’m guessing it’s because the calculation is happening on the width of element instead and the browser is never dividing an uneven number of pixels.</p><pre><code>  .lynns-burgers {
    position: fixed;
    left: 50%;
    top: 50%;
    transform: translate(-50%,-50%);
  }
</code></pre>
<p>But THEN, the character artwork started doing the vibration thing. Oy. The issue here was position values being calculated as decimals. I needed to make sure each <code>calc()</code> would return a whole pixel value, even as the custom properties changed.</p><p>So that would ultimately end up looking something like this:</p><pre><code class="language-css">  /* set custom properties */
  @media screen and (max-height: 900px) {
    :root {
      --mouth-base: 100px;
    }
  }
  @media screen and (min-height: 901px) {
    :root {
      --mouth-base: 150px;
    }
  }

  /* calculation multipliers should be even */
  .mouth
    place(0, $mouth-2,  calc(var(--mouth-base) * 1.14), calc(var(--mouth-base) * .52), -3deg)
    place(1, $mouth-12, calc(var(--mouth-base) * 1.16), calc(var(--mouth-base) * .52),  5deg)
    place(2, $mouth-14, calc(var(--mouth-base) * 1.18), calc(var(--mouth-base) * .50),  5deg)
    ...
</code></pre>
<h2>That’s it! Sort of.</h2><p>Looking through the final files and writing it all out makes it seem like so. much. (And there’s a lot I didn’t include here.) But it was definitely a process of discovery. I’m certain there are more efficient ways to do this, but that’s for another day.</p><img class="border" src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/lynnandtonic-2018.jpg" alt=""><small class="footnote">The finished site!</small><h2>An Archive</h2><p>Oh! I also added an archive featuring <em>every</em> version of this site dating back to 2007. It was super fun to look back through them. I still love every one of them so much. You can <a href="/archive">view them all in their dated glory here</a>.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/lynnandtonic-2018-archive.jpg" alt=""><h2>Whew, so… why all that?</h2><p>As usual, I wanted to try some new things and make something that might bring some joy to the web (it’s been a long year). <a href="/thoughts/entries/why-do-work-without-a-practical-purpose/">Here’s a good reminder</a> of why I do work like this.</p><p>I’ve been spending a lot of time in Illustrator lately. I recently redid some <a href="https://css-tricks.com/snippets/css/complete-guide-grid/">CSS grid</a> and <a href="https://css-tricks.com/snippets/css/a-guide-to-flexbox/">flexbox diagrams</a> for CSSTricks and I’m working on a top secret illustration project with Heroku. You might say I’ve been in an illustratin’ mood.</p><p>I’ve never done frame animation like this and it was an insightful introduction. Wow, the patience it requires!</p><p>I was also able to gain some experience optimizing my Illustrator workflow, vector artwork, and exported SVGs. I got to dabble with CSS properties (so cool) and with PostCSS (also very cool).</p><p>And best of all I had fun with it. I hope you have fun with it too. Until next year!</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/case-study-2018-refresh/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/case-study-2018-refresh/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Thoughts from Phoenix Design Week 2018</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>A few thoughts and highlights from this year’s Phoenix Design Week conference <em>Beyond Design</em>. But first, the rad intro video by the folks at <a href="https://magnetry.com/">Magnetry</a> in Phoenix:</p><div class="video-container wide"><iframe width="100%" src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/293427065" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><p><a href="http://marshallshore.blogspot.com/">Marshall Shore</a>, the hip historian, emceed beautifully and shares my love for Arizona. As someone who usually dresses to blend in, I can appreciate his dramatic sartorial choices. Those jackets! So great.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/phxdw-marshall-shore.png"><hr><h3>Armin Vit, <a href="https://underconsideration.com/">Under Consideration</a>, <a href="https://www.underconsideration.com/brandnew/">Brand New</a></h3><p>The thing I found most fascinating about Armin’s talk was his utilization of unconventional materials. When creating custom conference materials he and his wife, <a href="https://underconsideration.com/about/">Bryony Gomez-Palacio</a>, explored mold-making, <a href="https://www.behance.net/gallery/70707339/2018-Brand-New-Conference-Identity">cement curing</a>, and <a href="https://underconsideration.com/favorite_things_weve_made/2016-brand-new-conference-identity/">screen printing on vinyl records</a> and <a href="https://underconsideration.com/favorite_things_weve_made/2017-brand-new-conference-identity/">highly reflective materials</a>. They made a lot of their materials tirelessly by hand. My favorite quote by Penn Jillette comes to mind here. He even admitted it can be hard to collaborate with others (besides his wife) because not many can match their pace and obsession.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/phxdw-armin-vit.png"><p>Process-wise, he’s not a great sketcher. He moves quickly from a “shitty” sketch into the domain he’s mastered, Adobe Illustrator. Sometimes it makes sense to jump right in. He has an interesting approach to file setup, working from the top left corner of an artboard down and to the right as he iterates. This creates a neat timeline of thoughts and trials, keeping the latest version always on the bottom right of the file. Here’s a sad, quick recreation of that:</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/phxdw-illustrator-sketch.png"><blockquote>I’m a fucking beast at Illustrator. I own it. Except actually I rent it from Adobe.<cite>Armin Vit</cite></blockquote><hr><h3>Anne Yoachim, <a href="http://small.tulane.edu/our-team/leadership/ann-yoachim/">Tulane School of Architecture</a></h3><p>Anne’s work is fascinating: designing for specific communities in New Orleans and implementing physical solutions in real spaces. Her team worked on visual communication surrounding Hurricane Katrina, set up a community book center for underserved youth, and started a <a href="http://rubarbike.com/">community bike shop</a> where kids can learn to build and fix bicycles together.</p><p>With her work in the community as examples, she encouraged us to examine the relationships between all the roles we play. What are the biases we benefit from and inject into our work? What power dynamics are in place?</p><blockquote>Design is a capacity builder for companies… but it can’t solve everything.<cite>Anne Yoachim</cite></blockquote><hr><h3>Shari Benko, Experience Designer</h3><p>In another talk about recognizing bias, <a href="http://www.sharibenko.com/">Shari Benko</a> spoke on the relationship between UX and AI. In a field where you’re teaching a system to make decisions, how can you be as transparent as possible? How do you predict behaviors of the people interacting with it? She posed this question which I’ve been thinking about a lot ever since:</p><blockquote>How do you design for distrust?<cite>Shari Benko</cite></blockquote><hr><h3>Nakita M. Pope, <a href="http://brandingchicks.com/">Branding Chicks</a></h3><p>Nakita is a ray of sunshine and pure charisma. Branding is not a specialty of mine, but she makes it super relatable. She has a personal, one-to-one approach to branding and identity and compares it to counseling:</p><blockquote>You can help people figure out who they are and most importantly, you can give them permission to be fully themselves.<cite>Nakita M. Pope</cite></blockquote><hr><h3>Steve Thompson, Disney</h3><p><a href="https://www.instagram.com/sthompsonart/">Steve Thompson</a> talked about getting a gig at Disney and how his career path really started with a foundation in life drawing. An influential teacher in his past encouraged him to “draw from life.” It was this back-to-basics approach that’s helped him throughout all the turns of his career. It’s easy to forget about the foundations, but sometimes the simple stuff is what we need to solve hard problems.</p><p>He’s got an effortless, natural drawing style and I just love it.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/phxdw-steve-thompson.png"><p>He also shared the inspiration he’s gained from taking circus class and mastering trapeze. It’s amazing the confidence we can achieve through other ventures outside of our work. It may seem unrelated, but it all affects the work we do and the way we can be fully ourselves. </p><hr><h3>Jon Arvizu, <a href="https://jonarvizu.com/">Illustrator + Designer</a></h3><p>I found Jon’s honesty refreshing, speaking about the challenges of running your own business: navigating legal documents, protecting intellectual property, pushing against a lack of motivation, and the stress of leaving things unfinished.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/phxdw-jon-arvizu.png"><p>He’s an illustrator and printmaker and his work is really fun. I especially loved his Arizona-themed work (of course).</p><hr><h3>Cat Swetel, Lost Embossing Consulting</h3><p><a href="https://www.catswetel.com/">Cat Swetel</a>’s talk was a breakdown of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A3_problem_solving">A3 problem solving technique</a>, but what I found most interesting was the portion about reframing the problems we’re trying to solve. We often come at problems with a solution already in mind.</p><p>She gave the example of feeling thirsty. Some may frame the problem as “I don’t have a glass of water.” which is too specific. It already has a solution built in. A better framing of the problem is “I’m dehydrated.” which could be solved in a number of ways.</p><p>A good lesson in taking a step back and observing, noticing what we may have overlooked, and adjusting our thought process.</p><hr><h3>Lisa Peña, The Design School at ASU</h3><p>Lisa should really give a talk on the main stage next year. Her talk on design awareness had a lot of practical and insightful examples of how we “unconsciously omit groups from our designs” and how we can recognize our biases and design better experiences.</p><p>A few examples she spoke about:</p><ul><li><a href="https://youtu.be/LhpUJRGrZgc">Rainbow Bagel Quest</a> shows the time and effort it took for Zach Anner, a person with cerebral palsy, to obtain an elusive rainbow bagel</li><li>Burger King asks the American Sign Language (ASL) community to <a href="https://youtu.be/1akWJ2fiems">create a sign for the Whopper</a></li><li>Toyota’s <a href="https://youtu.be/2DhI7D5sS5U">Mobility for All campaign</a><li><a href="https://youtu.be/dKCdV20zLMs">Sesame Street introduces Julia</a>, a muppet with autism</li></li><li>Tennessee Tourist Development installs <a href="https://youtu.be/zi7R66sgvfU">scenic viewfinders for people with colorblindness</a> to experience the state’s natural beauty</li></ul><hr><h3>Aaron Draplin, Draplin Design Co.</h3><p>A peek at Draplin’s new book <em>Pretty Much Everything</em>:</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/phxdw-draplin.jpg"><p>Draplin is of course incredibly prolific and showcased that with gusto here. He spoke with passion about how any little thing in our lives—yard sale signs, birthday invites, funeral pamphlets—can become deeply personal, well-designed creative endeavors.</p><p>He’s certainly a unique communicator, full of energy and misdirection. The kind of person with a story about everything.</p><hr><p>It would be remiss of me to not mention I also gave a talk at this year’s event. There was no video captured, but I plan to post slides and maybe a narrated slideshow soon. Stay tuned.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/thoughts-from-phxdw-2018/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/thoughts-from-phxdw-2018/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Why give a conference talk? But also, why not.</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/lynnandtonic-conf-talk-guide.jpg" alt="@lynnandtonic’s Guide to Conference Talk Prep: 1. Thesis 2. Outline 3. Steam clean floors 4. Watch entire season of Scandal 5. Sob quietly 6. Slides"></p><p>Earlier this month I was deciding whether I should speak at a developer conference in the fall and found myself waffling between a pros and cons list. Turns out I ❤️ giving conference talks <em>and</em> I also don’t?</p><p>Every talk I’ve ever given was ultimately worth doing and I feel so, so grateful for each of those opportunities. But let’s be honest; prepping, traveling for, and giving a quality talk takes <em>work</em>, physically and emotionally.</p><p>This breakdown of benefits and drawbacks helped me think through the “why?” and “why not?” of speaking this time around.</p><h2>Truly great benefits</h2><p><strong>Learning</strong><br>Prepping a talk requires research and double and triple checking facts. Writing a loose script for others to experience helps me better understand and articulate my process and perspectives. Nothing helps me master a topic like teaching it.</p><p><strong>Personal growth</strong><br>Getting up on stage is <em>scary</em>. Public speaking is no joke in the fear department. Every time I do it, it becomes less intimidating and I become more confident.</p><p><strong>Visibility</strong><br>Giving talks helps introduce new people to my work. These are folks who I may never have met or reached in any other way. It’s super cool to see my projects’ traffic spike after a talk or to see my work shared anew on social media.</p><p>And although I’m not looking for a job, it’s helpful when potential employers have seen me speak or are already familiar with my work.</p><p><strong>Credibility</strong><br>Whether it should or not, our industry values speaking at conferences. Having talks on my resume or videos/slides to point to increases my credibility with peers, clients, and with future conferences I might want to speak at too.</p><p><strong>Introvert assist</strong><br>Chatting with people at large events can cause anxiety for me, especially if I’m attending solo. Being a speaker is like having an invisible wingperson. People will come talk to me about the topic I chose. It alleviates a lot of the pressure of small talk. Plus, if there’s a speaker dinner, that’s also a less stressful setting for conversation.</p><p><strong>That Feeling</strong>™<br>After I’m done giving a talk, I feel <em>incredible</em>. It’s a combination of adrenaline, accomplishment, relief, and a whole bunch of other emotions. All the preparation and the stress and the worrying feel completely worth it. I try to hold on to That Feeling™ for as long as I can. It’s the #1 thing that convinces me to do another talk later on.</p><h2>But of course there are drawbacks too</h2><p><strong>Time</strong><br>Even for a 30 minute talk, it takes me months of prep. Research, outline, write, slides, practice. Repeat until the minute I’m on stage. The majority of this work is done outside of my day job hours and a lot of conferences don’t pay their non-keynote speakers. So it can be a significant free time commitment.</p><p><strong>Stress</strong><br>Even if I feel fully prepared, every moment until the talk is completed I’ll feel stressed out. I’ll be thinking about the talk while in the shower, when I’m out with friends, and OMG I should be working on my talk instead of watching this episode of The Office for the 76th time.</p><p>If I have a lot of other emotionally demanding plans, the stress of a talk can be too much. Or it can cancel out the relaxation I hope for during a vacation.</p><p><strong>Visibility</strong><br>On the flipside, sometimes greater visibility can be harmful. Being in the spotlight provides opportunity for negative attention, creepers, or harassment.</p><p>Sometimes the last thing I want is for a large group of people to be looking at me or my work and I know that’s not the season for doing conference talks.</p><p><strong>Introvert kryptonite</strong>.<br>Although being a speaker assists in conversation, it also can be super draining. The stresses of traveling, speaking, and full days of lots of people can leave me ready for a 24-hour nap. I sometimes need to skip the closing party when my talk is scheduled for later in the day. Planning some time to recover is a must for me.</p><h2>Why or why not?</h2><p>After thinking things through <em>a lot</em>, I ultimately decided to decline the invitation even though it would have provided a free trip to Europe (oof) and would have been, as I was reminded by friends and family, Good For My Career (double oof). With FOMO ever-present, it can seem like a no brainer to say “yes.”</p><p>Sometimes “yes” is absolutely the right answer, and other times “no” is just as right for me. I know I’ll find another opportunity to speak if/when I feel up for it. And if you’re thinking of giving a conference talk, I do hope you find the right event for you. &lt;3</p><p>--</p><p><em>This was originally published on <a href="https://blog.andyet.com/2018/04/24/why-give-a-conference-talk-but-also-why-not">blog.andyet.com</a>.</em></p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/why-give-a-conference-talk-and-why-not/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/why-give-a-conference-talk-and-why-not/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Why do work without a practical purpose?</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>The first website I ever made was a fansite for a local Phoenix band called 17FourEyes. I was <em>obsessed</em> and compiled everything I knew about them, including transcribing the lyrics to their songs from demos and an eventual EP (I found out later I got a lot wrong). Through the site’s forum I connected with another fan where we gushed together and we eventually started hanging out at their shows. It was just so cool and got me hooked on the magic of the web.</p><p>Fifteen years later you could argue that most of my projects are still glorified fansites. Digital love letters to <a href="https://a.singlediv.com">CSS</a>, <a href="https://airportcod.es">airports</a>, <a href="https://topchefstats.com">reality cooking competitions</a>, and my home state of <a href="https://why.az">Arizona</a>.</p><p>I joke that I pride myself on creating projects that compel people to post on the internet asking “Why do this?” I recognize my work isn’t for everyone. As recently as last week a friend of mine, who no doubt gets <em>me</em>, said about the popularity of my <a href="https://airportcod.es">airportcod.es</a> project, “I just don’t get it.”</p><p>A lot of people question the practicality of the work or search for a deeper purpose:</p><blockquote>Just wondering, is there any legitimate reason for doing this?</blockquote><blockquote>Sure, it’s challenging, but why should anybody care?</blockquote><blockquote>Really nice but I really don't see the point.</blockquote><blockquote>Nice one, but WHY??</blockquote><p>My CSS drawing project, <a href="https://a.singlediv.com">a.singlediv.com</a>, is usually on the receiving end of the “Why?”, but my <a href="/thoughts/entries/case-study-2017-refresh">recent portfolio redesign</a> brought a fresh set of questioning.</p><p>My prepared goto answer is that these projects are just for fun and hey, it’s fun to do things that are weird. While technically true, there’s so much more I’m trying to do.</p><p>So… why then?</p><p>Why do we create art at all? Some artists create solely for themselves as a means of introspection and self expression. I truly love that. However, I’m not one of those artists.</p><p>I begin my process thinking about who will consume my work and how I hope they’ll respond to it. Art does not exist in isolation and it gains meaning from the people who experience it. It cannot be separate from the context in which it was created and the history of work that came before it. Those who view and participate in the work gain (or sometimes lose) something too.</p><h2>Seeing</h2><p>Have you ever had a friend send you an image and they say “This is incredible!”? You look at it. It has nice lighting I guess? What’s the big deal? “No, no. It’s not a photo. It’s a 12-foot oil painting.” In a small, special moment you aren’t sure if your eyes are playing tricks on you. “Whaaat?”</p><p>I <em>love</em> that feeling. Where someone’s work makes you question your reality. It begs you to dig deeper into how they did it. You want to, or in the best cases, <em>must</em> look closer. Imagine creating something that causes a tiny explosion in someone’s brain. When people view my work, I hope they might say “I didn’t know this was possible.”</p><p>Similarly, I love when someone’s work opens your eyes to something that was <em>always there</em>. A tool used in a new way, a pattern you never noticed, or the story behind a name. In an instant, this everyday thing is suddenly <em>different</em> and you can’t unsee it. The response I hope for in this case is, “Oh wow. Of course.”</p><p>Being surprised, stretching our imaginations, seeing things differently. Each an intention of the work and something I gain personally from creating it.</p><p>Experiences like this (as a viewer and a creator) are super valuable for me, especially long term. Every day we’re learning things that will be practical <em>someday</em>. You may not even realize you’re building this complex web of knowledge. We call it “intuition” but a big part of being an experienced designer/developer/whatever is how vast your web is and how effectively you can make connections between the disparate information and apply them to solve real problems.</p><h2>Challenging</h2><p>“Well, which is it? Art or design?!” a frustrated Redditor asks, trying to make sense of one of my projects. That question made me so happy. I want people who feel confused about what the work <em>is</em> to also question why they want to categorize it.</p><p>Designers do this a lot. I wish I had a piece of pizza for every “Design isn’t art” article I’ve seen. Art and design overlap in deep, meaningful ways and drawing a line between them does both a disservice. Also true for technology, where some want to draw the line even deeper. I want my work to blur the edges. I’m always amazed at the kind of magic we can create in the space where disciplines overlap.</p><p>Doing this work on the web specifically asks people to think about medium. I pay close attention when someone critiques art by saying the artist “must have a lot of time on their hands.” Almost always, it’s in response to work that’s made of unconventional material. Detailed portraits on Starbucks cardboard sleeves or styrofoam cups, landscapes constructed with thousands of matchsticks, drawings made with a single div and CSS. Very rarely does anyone say this about photography, oil painting, or stone sculpture.</p><p>What about a medium makes us value the time spent with it? I hope every person who views my CSS illustrations and says, “I can’t help but ask… why not just use SVG?” really does think about why. What would the work <em>be</em> if it was created in a format that’s obviously better suited? The medium we choose to work in is <em>part of the work</em> and contributes to its meaning.</p><h2>Sharing</h2><p>Lately the web can feel like an overwhelming sea of misery. (I won’t get into it. You know.) But it’s still such a joy to discover someone who shares in your weird, obsessive love for something. Maybe you stumble upon a website that feels like it was made just for you.</p><p>“Stumbling” upon something is such an important part of the web we take for granted. A huge contributor to a work of art’s meaning is how people access it. Does it exist in a physical space? Must you pay to enter that space and are the hours of access limited? Can people participate in it, contribute to it?</p><p>Connecting through art or shared passion is a gift and the web makes that possible at a scale unlike anything before. My little fansite turned a stranger into a friend, connecting on the web and at rock shows in the Nile basement. And that magic has only grown with every project since.</p><p>The joy we feel about the things we love is worth sharing and I encourage you to do it! You and the people viewing your work can benefit in a lot of ways, even if “the practicality of this is just non-existent.” 😉</p><p>--</p><p><em>This was originally published on <a href="https://blog.andyet.com/2018/01/24/why-do-work-without-a-practical-purpose">blog.andyet.com</a>.</em></p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/why-do-work-without-a-practical-purpose/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/why-do-work-without-a-practical-purpose/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Case Study: lynnandtonic.com 2017 refresh</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>Over the past ten years I’ve made ten different versions of my website. I call it my annual portfolio “refresh” since the content usually stays the same. I do always start with a blank CSS file.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/lynnandtonic-version-old.jpg"><small class="footnote">some past iterations of <a href="https://lynnandtonic.com">lynnandtonic.com</a></small><p>I do this each year for a few reasons:</p><ul><li>to ensure I’ll complete at least one non-work project</li><li>to experiment with and learn new techniques (a few standout refreshes were my first attempts at responsive design, flexbox, and this year, CSS grid)</li><li>a year is about the right amount of time for a version to exist where I don’t feel sad once I sit down to change it</li></ul><p>Also, a truly great thing about redoing my own site is that it’s fully mine and I can do whatever the heck I want. 😊</p><p>A very small percentage of my portfolio’s visitors are <a href="https://airportcod.es/">airport enthusiasts</a>, <a href="https://topchefstats.com/">Top Chef viewers</a>, and family (hi, mom). But the primary audience is overwhelmingly web designers, developers, and tech recruiters. These are people who know how websites are built and might take an extra minute to inspect things. I wanted to design around that.</p><h2>Concept and inspiration</h2><p>For years we’ve been telling the world that a website doesn’t need to look the exact same in every browser for every user. With responsive design and progressive enhancement, users <em>will</em> see things differently. Not everyone needs to experience the entirety of the site.</p><p>But could I make people <em>want</em> to experience all of it? Could I surprise them by taking these concepts to an absurd extreme?</p><p>I love to resize my browser and see how the layout responds and how the designer decided when things change and what gets dropped or added. I know lots of other people do this too. I initially thought I could subvert expectations by making the ubiquitous phone, tablet, and desktop breakpoints trigger completely different layouts with unique styles, colors, and type treatments. Three sites in one.</p><p>The changes, as dramatic as they might have been, still felt too conventional. You already expect something to happen at tablet size and then again for phones.</p><p>I’d recently watched a <a href="https://youtu.be/Vy2Vhnqtu8I">YouTube video</a> about the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuleshov_effect">Kuleshov Effect</a>, a term in film editing that describes “a phenomenon by which viewers derive more meaning from the interaction of two sequential shots than from a single shot in isolation.” A metaphorical bell chimed in my head.</p><p>There’s preexisting meaning for a site to have three (or a few more) distinct layouts: supporting common devices. But what would it <em>mean</em> for there to be 10, 15, or ultimately 21 distinct designs that “sit” side by side for you to discover one at a time, one after the other. Each one may be unremarkable on its own, but it’s the relationships (and differences) with the ones to the left/right and to the 18 others that make each one worth looking at.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/lynnandtonic-version-new.jpg"><small class="footnote">A preview of <a href="https://lynnandtonic.com">lynnandtonic.com</a></small><h2>Executing the idea</h2><p>I already knew it was possible to use CSS to turn basic markup into something extraordinary. <a href="http://www.csszengarden.com/">CSS Zen Garden</a> showed us this repeatedly for years. Another side project of mine, <a href="http://a.singlediv.com">a.singlediv.com</a>, takes this concept to ridiculous extremes (I sense a pattern here).</p><p>So executing this redesign started with basic HTML. One thing I’ve learned over the years of experimenting with CSS is you can achieve <em>a lot</em> without needing to sacrifice clean markup. Here’s what I landed on. The <code>&lt;span&gt;</code>s inside of the <code>&lt;h1&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;p class='intro'&gt;</code> would allow me to style each line differently if I needed and the <code>&lt;picture&gt;</code> element would allow for a responsive image plus provide additional <code>:before</code> and <code>:after</code> pseudo-elements (which <code>&lt;img&gt;</code> doesn’t allow).</p>
<pre><code>&lt;body class='home'&gt;
  &lt;nav class='main-nav'&gt;
    &lt;a class='nav-home' href='/'&gt;Home&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;a class='nav-web' href='/web'&gt;Web&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;a class='nav-art' href='/art'&gt;Art&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;a class='nav-about' href='/about'&gt;About&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;a class='nav-thoughts' href='/thoughts'&gt;Thoughts&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/nav&gt;

  &lt;h1&gt;
    &lt;span class='name'&gt;Lynn Fisher&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='desc'&gt;artist and designer from Phoenix, Arizona&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/h1&gt;

  &lt;p class='intro'&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;I make things for the web and for walls.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;I specialize in light-hearted projects that make people say, “I don’t get it.”&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;Yes, I’ve heard of SVG.&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;picture class='lynn'&gt;
    &lt;source srcset='/assets/images/lynn-small.png' media='(max-width: 1400px)'&gt;
    &lt;source srcset='/assets/images/lynn.png'&gt;
    &lt;img src='/assets/images/lynn.png', alt='a photo of the artist'&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
</code></pre>
<p>Also I guess I should add a disclaimer here. I’m the only one touching this code so I set things up the way that worked for me. Of course there are different and surely better ways of doing all of this. 🙂</p><p>I use Stylus for CSS preprocessing (and will in the following examples). I first created a <code>home.styl</code> where a reset and variables would be imported, basic page styles would be declared, and where the media queries would be set up. It, plus the other pages, would import into one <code>main.styl</code> that gets compiled and minimized. The structure looks like this:</p>
<pre><code>📁 _styl
  📁 components
  📁 globals
  📂 pages
    📄 about.styl
    📄 home.styl
    📄 thoughts.styl
    📄 work.styl
  📄 main.styl
</code></pre>
<p>I planned on using CSS grid for this redesign, so I created a super basic fallback layout to show by default (separated into its own file in a <code>home</code> directory) and I placed everything else inside a <code>@supports</code> declaration.</p>
<pre><code>📁 _styl
  📂 pages
    📂 home
      📄 fallback.styl
    📄 home.styl
  📄 main.styl
</code></pre>
<pre><code>/* home.styl */

@import 'home/fallback'

@supports (display: grid)
  body.home
    [base styles here]
</code></pre>
<p>If a browser doesn’t support <code>display: grid</code> it will render the fallback, which looks like this:</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/lynnandtonic-version-fallback.jpg"><p>With a fallback in place, I could now focus on the many different layouts. To keep things manageable, I split up each layout into its own file alongside the <code>fallback.styl</code> in the <code>home</code> directory (don’t mind my ridiculous naming).</p>
<pre><code>📁 _styl
  📂 pages
    📂 home
      📄 b-and-w-and-gold-all-over.styl
      📄 big-nav.style
      📄 big.styl
      📄 blockhead.styl
      📄 bolt.style
      📄 cutout.styl
      📄 diagonal.styl
      📄 disguise.styl
      📄 fallback.styl
      📄 fifty-fifty.styl
      📄 half.styl
      📄 L-Y-N-N.styl
      📄 landscape.styl
      📄 movie.styl
      📄 pop-out.styl
      📄 rotate.styl
      📄 stranger.styl
      📄 third.styl
      📄 triangle.styl
      📄 white-bars.styl
      📄 white-box.styl
      📄 x.styl
    📄 home.styl
  📄 main.styl
</code></pre>
<p>Then I was able to import each layout into its own media query:</p>
<pre><code>/* home.styl */

@supports (display: grid)
  body.home
    [base styles here]

  @media screen and (max-width: 400px)
    @import 'home/diagonal'

  @media screen and (min-width: 401px) and (max-width: 500px)
    @import 'home/L-Y-N-N'

  @media screen and (min-width: 501px) and (max-width: 600px)
    @import 'home/blockhead'

  + 18 more (2300px being the widest media query)
</code></pre>
<p>This removes any collisions that might happen and eliminates the need to do massive overrides. There is some repeated styling across various layouts, but I found that acceptable to keep things clear and organized. Each breakpoint is only using the CSS it needs for its specific layout.</p><h2>Further learning</h2><p>If you’re interested in digging into the CSS a bit more or to inspect individual layouts, I made my repo <a href="https://github.com/lynnandtonic/lynnandtonic.com">public on GitHub</a>. 🙈</p><p>I won’t go into how to use grid here as <a href="https://twitter.com/rachelandrew">Rachel Andrew</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/jensimmons">Jen Simmons</a> have written and spoken extensively on the topic. See Rachel’s <a href="https://gridbyexample.com/">Grid by Example</a> and Jen’s <a href="http://labs.jensimmons.com/">Experimental Layout Lab</a> as good places to start.</p><p><a href="https://twitter.com/patrickbrosset">Patrick Brosset</a> of Mozilla created a video breaking down the use of grid for one of my site’s layouts which is pretty cool:</p><div class="video-container wide"><iframe width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wmhYScbIxYk?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>></iframe></div><p>I planned on elaborating on some of my favorite parts of the redesign here, but I think I want people to be surprised as they explore. So if you haven’t checked it out yet, please do at <a href="https://lynnandtonic.com">lynnandtonic.com</a>.</p><h2>Response</h2><p>I always hope my work will inspire people to think about their medium and tools differently and to encourage them to experiment with what’s possible.</p><p>The response has been overwhelming and it’s truly wonderful to see people discovering and enjoying the site. I’m so grateful for everyone’s kind and encouraging words.</p><p>One piece of feedback I received is that a lot of people don’t resize their browsers at all. That’s true! And it’s totally okay. The site is still functional even if you don’t know any of the other layouts exist. Well, to be fair, there is one layout that would make for a super confusing experience (<em>Stranger Things</em> fans might know which one I’m talking about). But with my audience in mind, I figured risk was low.</p><p>With most of my work, there are people who ask “Why do this?” I have another post in the works that dives into the many reasons, but for now: sometimes it’s fun to do things that are weird.</p><p>Thanks for checking out the site. It means the world.</p><p>--</p><p><em>This was originally published on <a href="https://blog.andyet.com/2018/01/09/case-study-lynnandtonic-refresh">blog.andyet.com</a>.</em></p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/case-study-2017-refresh/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/case-study-2017-refresh/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Alignment</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/alignment.jpg" alt="illustration of tools"></p><p>This winter I visited the Wizarding World of Harry Potter in Orlando, Florida where they recently added a new portion of theme park and a ride inside Gringotts Bank. We zig-zagged in line outside for 30 minutes, anxious to see what the bank looked like from the inside. The <a href="http://yet.createsend1.com/t/r-l-ejrhtjk-l-h/">outside looked incredible</a> so we knew the inside would be even more magical. And it was.</p><p>When we finally entered the bank interior, we were transported, enchanted in every last detail. Within every nook there was something different to discover. We stopped in our tracks. And then, at the front of the line, a park employee started yelling. “DO NOT STOP! DO NOT STOP TO TAKE PICTURES! PLEASE KEEP MOVING!” Every 30 seconds it was the same message at top volume. I couldn’t help but laugh. “Please don’t look at this spectacle we’ve created.”</p><p>It was an interesting contrast between creators and maintainers, a clear misalignment of goals. The park employee’s job is to maintain order and ensure the line keeps moving. But the environment begs people to stop and look closer. In our own work, how do we establish alignment of values and communicate our goals? It’s crucial for team members working on a project and especially valuable for the future team mates we haven’t met yet, who will care for our work after we’re finished.</p><p>--</p><p><em>This was originally published in <a href="http://createsend.com/t/r-6C4ADAFBE3116E7C2540EF23F30FEDED">&amp;yet’s &amp;you newsletter</a>.</em></p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/alignment/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/alignment/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Design for developers and where to start</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/blog-design-shrug.jpg"><small>Infomercial narration voice: Is this you when it comes to design?</small><p>I talk a lot about designers learning development and in most discussions someone will inevitably ask, “Well, should developers learn design?” And to that I say, “Absolutely.”</p><p>A great deal of development work already <em>is</em> design work (don’t let anyone tell you differently). But I also know developers want to improve their visual design, UX, typography, and illustration skills. Here’s some tips on how to get started. Spoiler: They’re all things you can already do.</p><h2>Decide</h2><p>The first step is to decide to be a designer. It’s possible to design things without realizing it. But it doesn’t do any good designing things and continuing to deny that’s what you’re doing. Decide to be a designer and design <em>with</em> purpose and <em>on</em> purpose.</p><h2>Start</h2><p>Where do you start? Anywhere. There’s no standard curriculum or single point of entry. Pick a thing that interests you and start there. Don’t worry about what you need to know “first.”</p><h2>But maybe start small</h2><p>Just like with development, there’s a lot out there to learn and even more you may not need right now. It’s easy to be overwhelmed. Create content or time constraints to make things more manageable. Pick a tiny portion of a larger concept to focus on or set aside 10 minutes each day to read about a specific topic.</p><h2>Practice</h2><p>Practice makes better. Just like with development, you’ll learn how to make design decisions through repetition, experimenting, and of course by making mistakes.</p><h2>Recognize shared values</h2><p>Here’s a not-so-secret secret: The skills, practices, and values that make you a great developer are what make a great designer, too. Think of the things you prioritize that make your code better. Things like consistency and modularity. You want your code to have clear hierarchy, to be readable and easily understood. It should be flexible, testable, and accessible. Designers prioritize these same values when creating solid user experiences, interfaces, style guides, and brand identities. We have much more in common than you might think.</p><h2>Talk to designers</h2><p>If you’re still skeptical of where these commonalities lie, try talking to designers. Really. Turns out people like to talk about their work and passions, so ask. And then listen. A big part in learning anything is understanding and appreciating those who do it. And this has a cool ripple effect. The second you ask someone to help you learn, you’ve turned them into a teacher.</p><h2>Partner up</h2><p>If you can, find a designer who also wants to learn about development. Team up on some projects where you can help each other grow. Find out how the decisions you both make affect each other’s work. Think about how your unique perspective can impact theirs and vice versa.</p><h2>Show others your work</h2><p>This might be the scariest one. When you design something, show someone. Ask for feedback. Things may not feel finished or good enough to show, but that’s the time you most need to. I’ve been stuck on this quote by <a href="https://andyet.com/team/gar/">Gar</a> for years:</p><blockquote>Only those who are willing to take the risk of writing code that’s not perfect ever write code.</blockquote><p>You’re already sharing your code in various states of “done”; apply that same mindset to your design work.</p><h2>Stop apologizing</h2><p>Avoid the temptation to preface your work, questions, or discussions with “Sorry, I’m not a designer…” <strong>Stop apologizing.</strong> “You’re not a real designer unless you [insert some arbitrary condition].” Don’t say this to yourself and don’t let others say it to you. We define who we are and what we’re good at. If you’re designing things, you’re a designer.</p><h2>Level up</h2><p>Here’s the thing. As you do the things listed above and learn more about design, you’ll become a more versatile, empathetic, and well-rounded developer, too.</p><p>--</p><p><em>This was originally published on <a href="https://blog.andyet.com/2016/02/16/design-for-devs-where-to-start/">blog.andyet.com</a>.</em></p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/design-for-developers-and-where-to-start/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/design-for-developers-and-where-to-start/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>UX and WebRTC blog series</title>
      <description><![CDATA[A series of blog posts I wrote for &yet and AT&T about creating an awesome user experience when working with WebRTC in your application. See the <a href="https://blog.andyet.com/2016/01/21/att-webrtc-ux-series/">list of articles on &yet’s blog</a>.]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://blog.andyet.com/2016/01/21/att-webrtc-ux-series/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.andyet.com/2016/01/21/att-webrtc-ux-series/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>CSSDay Talk: Illustration with CSS</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>In December I gave a talk at <a href="http://cssday.io/">CSSDay</a> in Chandler, AZ. It focused on CSS illustration and my recent <a href="https://a.singlediv.com">A Single Div</a> project. It was an awesome one-day event and I hope there will be more like it in the future. I love me some CSS conferences, especially ones in my home town!</p><p>Here’s the video and slides for my talk. The rest of the talks (many of which were just wonderful) can be seen here: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EYymXZtpU0g&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;list=PLfWvsMtBxHo1WqPrBwxq3zc2RDo5HkYwy">CSSDay Talks playlist on Youtube</a>.</p><div class="video-container wide"><iframe width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/l7VUhEdM2aY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div><div><script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="d4bc493f50c24cdf910bb80aa4dd77da" data-ratio="1.6" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script></div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/talk-illustration-with-css/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/talk-illustration-with-css/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Highlights and quotes from Phoenix Design Week Method + Madness</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>This weekend was Phoenix’s annual design conference, Method + Madness. It’s always an awesome gathering of inspiring designers and good people. With no intention of fully capturing what went down, here are a few highlights and favorite quotes from the event.</p><blockquote>A community is a large collection of relationships.<cite><a href="https://twitter.com/michaelduah">Michael Duah</a></cite></blockquote><p>Illustrator Becky Simpson shared the process and humor that went into her book <a href="http://beckymsimpson.com/index/#/idratherbeshort/"><em>I’d Rather Be Short</em></a>. Charming and hilarious.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/becky-simpson.jpg"><blockquote>For every bad drawing there’s a good drawing around the corner.</blockquote><blockquote>Measure by progress not comparison.<cite><a href="http://beckymsimpson.com/">Becky Simpson</a></cite></blockquote><p>Stewart Scott-Curran threw out his talk the night before and flew slide-less by giving an honest talk about people and connecting on a human level.</p><blockquote>There’s no substitute for real flesh and blood connection.</blockquote><blockquote>Make friends not a network.<cite><a href="http://onlymoreneverless.com/">Stewart Scott-Curran</a></cite></blockquote><p>Illustrator Jacqui Oakley walked us through her process from original direction to execution, going from pencil sketches to acrylic painting and inking final touches. I especially loved the book covers she’s done including <a href='http://jacquioakley.com/skull-the-inferno-collection'>The Inferno Collection</a> and <a href='http://jacquioakley.com/anne-of-green-gables'>Anne of Green Gables</a>.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/jacqui-oakley.jpg"><blockquote>Start with something you’re good at and continue on to the work around it.</blockquote><blockquote>The good thing about collaboration is it gets you off your ass.<cite><a href="http://jacquioakley.com/">Jacqui Oakley</a></cite></blockquote><p>Designer Juan Carlos Pagan showcased some really sweet found-object letterforms made from <a href='http://www.carlospagan.com/portfolio/new-york-lottery-holiday-2012/46'>holiday lights</a> and <a href='http://www.carlospagan.com/portfolio/new-york-lottery-money-type/37'>stacks of cash</a>. Most interesting was <a href='http://www.carlospagan.com/portfolio/the-drinkable-book/9'>The Drinkable Book</a>, a book whose pages provide clean drinking water by filtering out waterborn bacteria. I could have listened to a talk just on that.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/drinkable-book.jpg"><blockquote>Create a world in which you have permission to do what you want to do.</blockquote><blockquote>Sometimes you have to throw your hat over the fence so you are forced to go get it.<cite><a href="http://www.344lovesyou.com/">Stefan Bucher</a></cite></blockquote><p>Stefan Bucher gave a super unique talk about an exhibition he created called <a href="http://www.344lovesyou.com/projects/everything/"><em>Everything Is Going Exactly As Planned</em></a>. It examines his work from the near and distant future. It bordered on performance art and the Q&A session turned into a display of improv. I loved it.</p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/stefan-bucher.jpg"><blockquote>Show people what things <em>could be</em> in real life.</blockquote><blockquote>When our resources are limited it makes way for creativity and ingenuity.<cite><a href="http://alexmedina.co/">Alex Medina</a></cite></blockquote><p>Ashleigh Axios, Creative Director at the White House, gave a talk pretty much only she could give. She spoke about her digital strategy team, the first of its kind for a Presidential administration, and being “on the front lines of changing the way people interact with the people they’ve elected.” Many of her points aligned perfectly with <a href='https://andyet.com'>&yet</a>’s values of “people first” and “tiny leadership.”</p><blockquote>If your goal is not out of reach, then it’s not a goal; it’s a task.<cite><a href="https://twitter.com/AshleighAxios">Ashleigh Axios</a></cite></blockquote>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/highlights-and-quotes-from-phxdw-2015/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/highlights-and-quotes-from-phxdw-2015/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>On making design decisions</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>Articulating our decision making is a huge part of our jobs as designers. Every day we should be asking ourselves “Why did I decide to do it this way?” Our coworkers, clients, and users will be asking the same question, so we may as well be prepared.</p><p>Everything we add or leave out is the result of decision making. Sometimes we’re called to explain decisions around entire layouts and other times it’s just the exact shade of grey we chose for a horizontal rule. Big or small, it’s important to understand <em>why</em> we land on the solutions we do.</p><p>Below are six common decision patterns I’ve seen in my time as a designer. Note that these aren’t specifically ordered and I’m not suggesting any one is best. It’s important first to recognize our behavior before deciding what makes the most sense for our project which, as always, depends.</p><h2>Decisions made by other people</h2><p>On every project there will be plenty of decisions that have already been made for us. Most commonly this shows up as existing branding, usage rules, and style guides. An important decision we make is whether or not to adhere to these guidelines, for better or worse.</p><p>Another way this pops up in our work is a client insisting on a certain direction, typeface, or various other treatment. How many times have you heard a designer say “That was the client’s decision” about negative feedback? Funny how we rarely use that one when the reviews are great. The truth is we made the decision that implementing their idea was better than continuing to push our idea or even to walk away from the project entirely. Decisions made by others are our decisions too.</p><h2>Decisions based on systems</h2><p>Designers and artists have been studying forms, trying new methods, and establishing systems for centuries. Many designers today use these proven systems to inform their decisions. <a href="http://alistapart.com/article/more-meaningful-typography">Typographic scales</a> determine proper size measurements and rhythm, the <a href="http://www.creativebloq.com/design/designers-guide-golden-ratio-12121546">Golden Ratio</a> influences aesthetic proportions, and the <a href="http://www.cambridgeincolour.com/tutorials/rule-of-thirds.htm">Rule of Thirds</a> helps create balanced and dynamic compositions. I like to call this type of decision <em>leaning on history</em>.</p><h2>Decisions based on personal history</h2><p>Another type of history we lean on is our own project history. We sometimes make decisions based on what we’ve personally seen succeed or fail in the past. What worked on a previous project may work swimmingly for this one or horribly for another. As we know, every project has its own set of constraints and complexities.</p><h2>Bandwagon decisions</h2><p>Many design decisions we make are influenced by what other people are doing. Copying what one designer is doing can be called plagiarism, but copying what lots of other designers are doing can be called “following industry trends.” There’s safety in numbers and making a bandwagon decision (following the path others have tested and approved) can make a lot of sense and save time. However, bandwagon decisions that reach ubiquity can lead to poor decisions about your specific project in the name of perceived standards. Love it or hate it, the <a href="http://digiday.com/publishers/the-problem-with-the-hamburger-menu/">hamburger menu</a> is a great example.</p><h2>Decisions based on data</h2><p>“Designed with science!” That’s how it can feel making design decisions based on data. Data gathered through user observation, interviews, and A/B testing can show us what’s working as intended and what isn’t. Decisions about which features to change or eliminate can naturally follow. Sometimes though, the data is poorly collected or it might not be very <em>meaningful</em>. Designing contrary to what the data might suggest is a decision too.</p><h2>Decisions based on intuition</h2><p>This type of decision can be hard to explain. It’s when we say something looks or feels “right.” A designer’s intuition is the sum of the observation, training, and practice they’ve accumulated over the length of their career. I suspect this is what people are referring to when they say someone has “a natural eye.” Sometimes there isn’t a specific system or data set or past project to point to. Sometimes the concept is brand new. This is when we make decisions based on intuition.</p><h2>Decide to decide</h2><p>Any single decision can be informed by a combination of these approaches and many more not listed here. It’s important to know why we make decisions, but also to not let that knowledge paralyze us. No decision might seem better than a bad one, but at least with a bad decision we’ve learned something.</p><p>If you’re a leader of a team, empower your designers (and your entire team, really) to make these hard decisions and to own the consequences. As much as indecision can damage a project or team, so can constantly asking for permission.</p><p>--</p><p><em>This was originally published on <a href="https://blog.andyet.com/2014/11/21/on-making-design-decisions">blog.andyet.com</a>.</em></p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/on-making-design-decisions/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/on-making-design-decisions/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Single Div Drawings with CSS</title>
      <description><![CDATA[A tutorial article walking through some techniques I used and examples from <a href="https://a.singlediv.com">a.singlediv.com</a>. Check it out on <a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/2014/09/single-div-drawings-with-css/">Mozilla Hacks</a>.]]</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://hacks.mozilla.org/2014/09/single-div-drawings-with-css/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://hacks.mozilla.org/2014/09/single-div-drawings-with-css/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>On giving my first-ever conference talk</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>I recently gave my first-ever conference talk titled “Developers as Intentional Designers” at <a href="http://2014.jsconfbr.org/">JSConf Brazil</a>. I prepared my content, practiced my talk in front of the mirror and friends, and researched public speaking. I found theses resources to be particularly helpful: <a href="http://ladiesintech.com/the-best-advice-on-public-speaking/">The best advice on public speaking</a>, <a href="http://bradfrostweb.com/blog/post/on-speaking/">Brad Frost: On Speaking</a>, <a href="http://speaking.io/">speaking.io</a>. In hopes of helping others and remembering for myself, here are a few things I did (or wished I did) and a few things I learned.</p><h3>You might regret agreeing to speak.</h3><p>It’s super exciting getting invited to speak at a conference or getting your talk proposal approved. Whew! Now you can focus your energy (and nerves) on practicing and giving your talk, right? But sometimes fear manifests in weird ways. One way you might experience is intense, emotional regret for signing up for this in the first place. In your mind you’ll know you can do it. But in your gut you absolutely won’t want to. The best way I learned to fight the urge to back out is to…</p><h3>Focus on the why as much as the what.</h3><p>There’s a lot of advice out there on what to speak about and even more about how to get through your talk. As much as you focus your time and energy on the content of your presentation and the spirit of your delivery, spend as much time reminding yourself and your audience why your talk matters. You might be filling a gap, pushing for a new way of thinking, or reminding people of things forgotten. Your thoughts are worth sharing. Remind yourself of this often.</p><h3>Practice doesn’t only happen in front of your computer.</h3><p>There were some nights and weekends where I just wanted to veg out and do nothing. I felt guilty. “I should be practicing my talk,” I’d tell myself. “I haven’t sat in front of my slides in a few days.” Well, it turns out practicing a talk isn’t limited to outlining, slide-making, and run-throughs. You’ll be thinking about your content all the time. You will run through your talk thousands of times while in the shower, watching television, and even during conversations with your husband (sorry, Clay!). Don’t beat yourself up for taking a nap in the afternoon or not spending your weekend flipping through your deck. You’re practicing without realizing it.</p><h3>The scale of your audience might not require a change in content, but it does require a change in <em>delivery</em>.</h3><p>I gave a dry-run of my talk to my friends at <a href="http://meltmedia.com">meltmedia</a> a week or so before the actual conference. It was in their office kitchen with my slides on a television and about 20+ people listening. The intimacy (and familiarity) of the people and environment made some parts feel forced and awkward. I had prepared those parts for an audience of ~150. I took note, and the same parts felt purposeful and right when speaking to a larger crowd with my slides projected huge on the wall behind me. Scale matters. Practicing in front of a small group is super beneficial, but keep your final audience in mind. Which is also a huge part of the next tip…</p><h3>Speak to the one person you want to hear your talk the most.</h3><p>It might be a real person you’ve worked with or it could be a symbolic persona. People will get varying degrees of value from your talk; some parts might speak to them and others might not. Think of the person who would benefit most from your talk, who would be the most changed after hearing it. Write your content with that person in mind and practice like you’re talking directly to them. You need to convince them of something. How would you present and deliver the content to do just that?</p><h3>Drink lots of freaking water.</h3><p>Seriously. I saw a few tips on keeping a water bottle nearby to keep your mouth from drying out. I think this is so important and something I wished I’d done. During my talk I felt like I had been gargling sand. Even a tiny sip of water would have been a lifesaver. Conference organizers, it would be amazing if you purposefully placed a bottle of water on the podium for each new speaker. Not necessary of course, but a delightful and helpful detail.</p><h3>Plan to arrive with plenty of time to spare.</h3><p>I planned on arriving to the conference hotel the night before the event. With a long and unexpected delay, I ended up arriving halfway through the conference. Luckily the schedule was flexible and they switched the time of my talk for later in the day (so so grateful for that). To avoid the stress and potentially missing your own talk, pad your arrival time, especially if you’re traveling internationally. Ask the conference organizers for travel tips or quirks for your destination.</p><h3>Practice with different display setups and memorize keyboard shortcuts.</h3><p>When you’re in front of a large group of people, you might forget how to use a computer. You know that feeling of not being able to type when someone is looking over your shoulder? Magnify that times 150. Practice with various display setups so you know just what to do when your displays are swapped or you’ve entered full-screen before you’re ready. In most cases a helpful audience member can shout out how to fix your problem, but it doesn’t hurt to be prepared.</p><h3>Practicing your talk won’t end once you’re off-stage.</h3><p>You might have heard that you won’t remember a lot of your talk. There’s this weird blackout your brain does during those 30 minutes. This totally happened to me. I don’t remember much of what I said at all. So for the next few days (and late nights) I ran through my talk over and over in my head. “Did I say that one part? I can’t remember.” I tested myself to see how much of my talk I still had memorized. “If I still remembered, I must have said it all, right?” If you’re able to, relax. In a few weeks you’ll need that energy to gather the courage to press “Play” on your talk’s video.</p><p>And lastly…</p><h3>Give yourself a pat on the back.</h3><p>It’s not easy to get up in front of your peers and give a talk, especially talks that require a ton of knowledge, preparation, and practice. You did it! Have a drink and celebrate.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/on-giving-my-first-ever-conference-talk/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/on-giving-my-first-ever-conference-talk/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Advice for young designers and future me</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p> Three things I’ve learned to be most valuable in my career thus far and that I remind myself every single day.</p><h3>Be kind.</h3><p> If you’re remembered for anything, make it kindness. We’d all like to be smart, talented, funny, successful, but don’t forget your top priority. Be good to those around you.</p><h3>Ask questions.</h3><p> Stay curious. Choose clarity over assuming. Don’t be afraid of not knowing the answer. Or looking dumb. If you want something, ask for it. You’ll be surprised at what others are willing to give.</p><h3>Share.</h3><p> Be as giving as you’d like others to be. Then share even more. Share the credit but not the blame. Generosity extends beyond money. How much of what makes you *you* are you willing to give others? Make it everything.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/advice-for-young-designers-and-future-me/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/advice-for-young-designers-and-future-me/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Good. Better. Best.</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p> A few weeks ago I tweeted this:</p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">It infuriates me when people say I can or should only be good at one thing. I&#39;ll be awesome at lots of things, thank you very much.</p>&mdash; Lynn Fisher (@lynnandtonic) <a href="https://twitter.com/lynnandtonic/status/387622415582253058">October 8, 2013</a></blockquote><script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script><p> While I think the tweet sums up my point pretty succinctly, I thought it might be good to elaborate.</p><p> We’ve all heard the arguments. With our limited time and energy, we should focus on being awesome at one thing. Let us not spread ourselves too thin or become jacks-of-all-trades but masters-of-none. It makes sense. I agree with this on some philosophical level. What I don’t like is how it’s applied.</p><p> I’ve observed this mantra of “doing one thing well” being used as a shield. It’s the perfect excuse to not learn that new skill or try that unknown project. And even worse, I’ve seen it used to <em>discourage</em> designers from learning how to code. Well, I’d like to politely respond with, “Fuck that.”</p><p> People are capable of so much. Be good at lots of things.</p><p> This conversation begs for more definition around the word “good”. Of course “good” is relative and that’s okay. What we should avoid are harmful comparisons.</p><p><em>“I’ll never be as good as so and so.”</em></p><p><em>“She’s better at this than I am.”</em></p><p><em>“I’m not the best person to do this work.”</em></p><p>Good. Better. Best.</p><p>....</p><p>A few months ago I couldn’t solve a Rubik’s cube to save my life. I decided I wanted to learn, so I looked up tutorials and sought advice from my friend Andy. It took weeks of practice, but I can now reliably solve the cube every time, with an average of about three minutes.</p><p> There are definitely people who can solve it faster and with fewer moves. And I’ll never be as good as Mats Valk, who recently solved it in 5.55 seconds. But for most Rubik’s cube scenarios I predict I’ll be involved with, I feel no guilt in saying I’m good at it. What’s an appropriate gauge? I’d be confident in having a team rely on me to solve one (as long as we have three minutes).</p><p>....</p><p>The truth is, in most businesses there’s a lot of work to be done and the difficulty of that work varies. The best person to do a task often isn’t the best person at that skill set. You’d likely not have a full-stack JavaScript developer building basic interactions on a static website. But you definitely could give that task to a designer who is good with JQuery. Not being the best shouldn’t deter us from learning skills that can contribute to our team and projects.</p><p>Yes, you may not be as good at development as someone who focuses solely on that. But wouldn’t it be great if you were a designer who could do both? Keep learning. Be better than you were yesterday. You may not be the best, but you can be awesome.</p><p>Learning new skills, even if you don’t think you’ll use them at your job, helps broaden our perspectives. Learn programming to better understand the developers we work with. Start writing to understand the process of content creators. There’s no better path to understanding than doing.</p><p>Here’s another tweet I 100% believe in.</p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I think every &quot;How to Work with X or Y Person&quot; article can be summed up with &quot;Understand them and appreciate them.&quot;</p>&mdash; Lynn Fisher (@lynnandtonic) <a href="https://twitter.com/lynnandtonic/status/373446534316048384">August 30, 2013</a></blockquote><script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script><p>Respect and appreciate your colleagues by learning what they do. Asking questions has an incredible ripple effect. The second you ask your colleague to help you learn, you’ve turned them into a teacher.</p><p>Who knows what the future will hold? Things are changing constantly, especially with the web. Don’t pass on opportunities to learn new things. You can be good at them. Curiosity and a passion for learning are qualities of a good designer. That alone will make you better, and probably the best kind of designer to work with.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/good-better-best/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/good-better-best/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>CSS is a designer’s medium</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p> Recently I’ve heard a lot of discussion and seen much consternation around expecting designers to write HTML and CSS. A common concern is the negative impact of splitting focus and energy between two skill sets. While I’m a realist about time and a supporter of specialization, I can’t help but feel a shift in perspective is what’s needed most. Try thinking of it this way: for web designers, design is the skill; CSS is the medium.</p><p> When people hear I like to paint, the first question they ask is “What medium do you use?” The second question they ask is “Why don’t you paint with oils?” People react differently based on the medium we choose. An artist who crushes and mixes her own oil pigments instead of using store-bought tubes. An artist who uses the most basic computer painting program to create pixelated masterpieces. An artist who draws photorealistic portraits with cheap ballpoint pens. Medium matters.</p><p> A frequent analogy thrown out is the architect. Is it reasonable for an architect to construct the building she designs? Could she possibly know how to wire the electrical, lay the foundation, etc. and could she do them well? Within the scope of HTML and CSS, I find this analogy lopsided in scale. For me, a more fitting analogy is the fashion designer, and the fashion designer’s medium is fabric.</p><p> Most fashion designers, like other disciplines, start by sketching an idea on paper. These sketches are usually gestural and exaggerated. They are important because they show the origin and evolution of a thought, allowing for quick visualization of a concept. And while the sketches on their own can be quite stunning and inspirational, they are not a dress and they can not be worn.</p><p> A beginning fashion designer likely sews his own designs. This often results from cost efficiency, but provides value no designer would want to miss. Selecting fabrics, working them in your hands, learning and understanding the behavior of the various types: these are benefits only gained through direct experience. The complement to sewing is fitting. The designer sees how the garment fits on a human body and adjusts the design. Flattery, comfort, and movement are all considered. The fitting step is crucial because clothes aren’t meant for a hanger; they are designed to be worn and <em>felt</em>.</p><p> As the fashion designer gains more experience and her business grows, she will sew less and direct more. She carries the vision and sets the path for designing entire collections. Designing at such a large scale is difficult, but is supported by years of experience working with fabrics, fitting on various bodies, trial and error, and customer feedback. Plus, you can bet she still regularly has her hands on those fabrics. And although she doesn’t construct the garments herself, she could.</p><p> For web designers, CSS is the medium. Sketching, wireframes, and comps are important pieces in the design process and, while often beautiful and inspirational, they are not a website. Writing HTML and CSS makes the design process tactile. The designer can memorize a list of rules all day, but nothing compares to the experience of moving things around and discovering the (sometimes surprising) behavior of the medium. And just like the fashion designer must fit a garment on a real human, so should web designers “fit” their designs in a real browser. After all, each browser wears our designs differently.</p><p> With more experience, designers can write less, direct more, and design larger and more complex interfaces. But they should still be touching the HTML and CSS regularly. The capabilities of the medium change and improve each day. More and more can be achieved with less.</p><p> CSS is a designer’s medium through which we execute our design expertise. I could list the many benefits I’ve experienced designing with HTML and CSS, but the most succinct reason I’ve seen is from Geoff Teehan in his post <a href="https://medium.com/what-i-learned-today/83bb0f329f43">Old Dog, New Trick</a>:</p><blockquote>It gets designers using their designs sooner. They’ll begin catching issues that were in their designs all along that were impossible to see. The issues are invisible. They need to be felt.</blockquote>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/css-is-a-designers-medium/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/css-is-a-designers-medium/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Why WhyAZ?</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/whyaz.jpg" alt="WhyAZ"></p><h2>So really, why?</h2><p>Earlier this year, friend and former meltmedian, Nick Crohn and I were discussing hiring challenges over lunch. The question of the day was, “How do we attract great talent to come to Phoenix and keep them here once they do?” We easily listed handfuls of reasons we love living here and it dawned on us. We spend a lot of time building up and promoting our brands and projects, but we spend little time talking about Arizona. Our state has a lot to offer and so <a href="https://why.az">why.az</a> was born.</p><h2>Our goals</h2><p>We wanted to avoid a sales pitch. Our first goal of WhyAZ was to share honest and real reasons why we love living and working in Arizona. To provide interesting, digestible information that many may be surprised or delighted to learn. Our second goal of WhyAZ was to make the site visually and technically interesting with hopes designers and developers might appreciate the aesthetic and examine how it’s built.</p><h2>The approach</h2><p>When deciding what approach to take, I thought a lot about what makes web design exciting for me. In May I attended <a href="http://cssconf.com/">CSSConf</a> in beautiful Amelia Island, Florida. One of the recurring themes was the blurring between design and development and utilizing CSS3, <a href="http://sass-lang.com/">Sass</a>, and browser tools to enhance our designs. With only a few lines of CSS, we can easily duplicate the intricate design work we’ve previously reserved for Creative Suite. As a designer who prefers to work in a text editor, it really is exhilarating to type words and numbers and see pictures come out the other side.</p><p>So I thought it might be neat if we designed the site completely in browser, drawing our graphical elements in CSS. I’d previously seen unbelievable CSS drawings, but always in the context of experimentation. And sometimes at the expense of clean, semantic markup. Could we create visually appealing illustrations while still maintaining the integrity of the content? I decided to draw the Arizona state flag to see.</p><p>Below are examples of three versions of the flag as seen in Google Chrome:</p><p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/whyaz-flags.jpg" alt="WhyAZ flags"></p><p>And here’s the markup it took to build them:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;!-- 1. flag with 4 HTMl elements --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;flag&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;flag-stripes--left&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;flag-stripes--right&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;flag-star&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- 2. flag with 3 HTML elements --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;flag-three&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;flag-stripes--left&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;flag-stripes--right&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- 3. flag with 1 HTML element --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;flag-one&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre><p>And for comparison, here’s how they look in Firefox and Safari, respectively (without vendor prefixes added).</p><p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/whyaz-flags-safari.jpg" alt="WhyAZ flags"></p><p>You can see the flags example here: <a href="https://why.az/flags.html">why.az/flags.html</a></p><p>The first option (4 HTML elements) worked best for us in this instance. This structure allowed for the best cross-browser support, easier CSS maintenance, and most consistent rendering. For the flag this seemed reasonable, but for the rest of the site, I decided to add tighter constraints. Each illustration could only be 2 HTML elements or less. This allowed our markup to look like this (acceptable by our standards):</p>
<pre><code>&lt;p class=&quot;icon starwars&quot;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;icon-img&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Star Wars&lt;/p&gt;
</code></pre><p>And here are a few examples of illustrations drawn with CSS and two or less HTML elements:</p><p><img src="https://lynnandtonic.com/assets/images/whyaz-examples.jpg" alt="WhyAZ example images"></p><h2>Lessons learned</h2><p>So what do we think now that we’ve done it? Drawing with CSS is not the most time efficient and not the best way to create graphical elements for a website. There are cross-browser rendering issues, stylesheet sizes, and maintainability to consider. With SVG, icon fonts, and responsive image solutions improving each day, our options for visually stunning, high-performance sites keep growing.</p><p>Even so, designing WhyAZ this way was incredibly fun. It forced us to think about shapes and layers in a new way, designing within tight constraints and with minimalism front of mind. And most exciting is how much we can achieve with simple HTML and CSS. To build a visually interesting, content-rich site, all you really need is a text editor and a browser.</p><p>And of course, see WhyAZ live in action at <a href="https://why.az">why.az</a>.</p><p>--</p><p><em>This was originally published on <a href="https://www.meltmedia.com/blog/why-whyaz">blog.meltmedia.com</a>.</em></p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/why-whyaz/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/why-whyaz/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Clients, water softeners, and “my nephew the designer”</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p> As designers, a common nightmare tale we resentfully tell is the client who consults his 15-year old nephew for design advice. We feel a whirlwind of betrayal, disgust, and pity. The go-to defense? “Your nephew is not a trained professional and I know better, trust me.” And we mean it.</p><p> On a related note, a few years ago I purchased a brand new water softener for my home in Chandler. I consulted a few companies with plenty of questions. How much salt do I put in? Do I use the granular salt or the tablets? And of course, how much does it cost to maintain? Amongst these companies, I heard every answer you can imagine. I even heard opposite answers from two people from the <em>same company</em>.</p><p> So I took to the interwebs. Surely there was a concrete answer published somewhere. But it was more of the same. The arguments over which salt to use were awkwardly heated. The tired consumer in me sighed, “It’s just freaking salt!” So what did I do? I asked my dad. He’s in no way a water treatment professional, but I trust him. And that’s all I needed to push me to a decision. To be honest, by that point, my 15-year old cousin could have swayed me with a semi-confident opinion.</p><p> I can only imagine this is woefully similar to the experience our clients have looking for a designer or firm to hire. Different designers tell them different information about the best way to do the work, how long it will take, and how much it will cost. And searching the internet for more concrete answers? Yikes. We can’t even agree on how to pronounce the word gif.</p><p> So five years later, after a few switches, I’ve settled on one water softener company. They wanted more than my business; they wanted my trust. And they knew it would take work. They were patient, clear, and honest, never taking advantage of my water softener ignorance. They followed up with me and remembered my past concerns. And after respectfully answering plenty of my “well my dad said…” questions, it wasn’t long before it flipped. Soon I was telling my dad, “well my water softener guys said…”</p><p>So the next time a client brings you feedback or comps from a “non-professional” family member or friend, take it and run with it. It’s a great opportunity. They aren’t trying to undermine you, they’re looking for someone to trust. With purpose and honesty, that can be you. And down the road, you’ll be the one they’re calling for help.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/clients-water-softeners-and-my-nephew-the-designer/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/clients-water-softeners-and-my-nephew-the-designer/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>High performance teams need more than talent</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>In its wildly revered culture document, Netflix compares itself to a pro sports team rather than a family. They “hire, develop and cut smartly” with the goal of having “stars in every position.” This makes the sports fan in me want to pump my fist in the air. I grew up playing year-round competitive basketball, and while it’s nothing like the NBA, it did teach me more about team dynamics than any team building exercise ever could.</p><p>The sports analogy works because it simplifies the problem and shows us a solution we’re not only familiar with, but that we connect with emotionally. However, I’ve seen this simplicity lead to a narrow-sighted interpretation: the cause of our team’s problems is we don’t have enough talent. It’s an idealist’s favorite phrase. “Just put a bunch of talented people in a room and they’ll produce great results.” But ask any sports coach or watch any inspirational sports film and you’ll realize talent alone does not make a high performance team.</p><p>When I was 14 I played on a district championship team. We played a quick, fast-break style of basketball and outran our opponents to victory. Our biggest rivals were arguably just as good, but played a controlled, highly-strategic game. For a traveling tournament we joined forces, building a team of five of their best with five of ours. Our two coaches were both great, so they decided to co-coach. As you may expect, we weren’t the powerhouse they predicted and ended the tournament without placing.</p><p>As good as our players were, we couldn’t perform together. A team not only needs a goal to run toward, but a collective commitment on how to get there. Our leadership was split and relied on our talent to fill in the gaps. No matter how talented, it’s difficult for a team to be highly productive if team members move in different directions.</p><p>Ever watch the NBA All-Star Game? If not, don’t worry. It’s actually quite boring. The problem is the teams are built with individual talents in mind; there isn’t balance. In the film <em>Miracle</em>, Herb Brooks is questioned about passing on many of the best players. He calmly states, “I’m not looking for the best players. I’m looking for the right ones.” He knew about the importance of balance and that each player changes the dynamic of the whole team.</p><p>Recently a long-time coworker of mine moved on to a new job. To sum up six years of back story, he and I were a team. And a highly productive one. While both of us are reasonably talented individually, it was our balance of skills that made us great together. His strengths made up for my weaknesses and where he dropped the ball, I was able to catch it. When talking about finding his replacement, it was obvious we couldn’t just drop anyone in and expect the same results. Because an oft-forgotten thing a team really needs is practice. And that takes time.</p><p>My last basketball example is one that’s stuck with me for years. While playing on my high school team, I retrieved a loose ball and was racing a single defender in a fast break. I probably could have made it to the hoop, but in a moment of reflex, I threw the ball over her head away from my target. My heart stopped. Did I just throw the ball away? But at that moment, my team mate pulled ahead of the defender, caught the ball, and scored uncontested.</p><p>That play exemplified what it felt like to be on a real team. We moved together. We didn’t need set plays and process and instead relied on instinct, engrained through hours and hours of practice. I trusted my team mate was there and she was.</p><p>Talent is the easiest qualification for a team and we have plenty of questions and tests to measure against. But building high performance teams is about more than gathering talented folks in a room. After all, proximity and shared work don’t make a team. Direction, balance, and trust do.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/high-performance-teams-need-more-than-talent/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/high-performance-teams-need-more-than-talent/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>I don’t know what I’m doing.</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p><em>Recently I was asked to speak to a group of high school students about my career path into web design and to offer any advice as they decide on a college and career path of their own.</em></p><hr><p>I was always good at school. I have a great memory, especially for spoken words, so lectures were a perfect medium. I was accustomed to acing tests and crushing papers.</p><p>But halfway through college I lost interest in my plan to become a film animator, and I spent the remaining years painting and metal welding with no expectation of a career in the arts. On the day of my graduation, ASU President Michael Crow asked me what I planned to do next. In a long line of graduates, I was the only one to answer, “I don’t know what I’m doing.”</p><p>And that there was the biggest shift I experienced in my post-school career. Gone were the days where what was expected of me was outlined in a syllabus or prerequisites list. This was most definitely scary, but it could be either exhilarating or crippling, and that choice was up to me.</p><p>....</p><p>Do you have a favorite teacher? Looking back on my schooling, I realize I had a one-of-a-kind, praise-your-deity, gem of a teacher. His name was Mr. Perry and he taught Honors World History. His class had the highest drop rate and it had nothing to do with tests or grading curves. His only requirement was to be fully engaged 100% of the time. There was no text book or syllabus. Each day was unpredictable, and every problem, discussion, or task he gave us had no clear correct answer. It was the hardest course I’d ever taken and the most similar to my life now as a professional.</p><p>....</p><p>Soon after graduation, I interviewed for a web developer position with meltmedia. As I sat there, all I could think to myself was, “I don’t know what I’m doing.” I’d previously made websites only as a hobby and quickly realized how little I actually knew about them. They saw potential in me and offered me the position (thanks!). And now six years and a few role changes later, I still regularly feel like I don’t know what I’m doing. In an industry that’s changing by the minute, it’s a strangely comforting constant.</p><p>My career path wasn’t planned out and was shaped by an acceptance that it’s okay not to know. Even now I don’t have much of a plan for what I’ll do next. All I know is I want to keep learning and to keep making things, and with that I’m confident I’ll find my way.</p><p>Most people feel like they don’t know what they’re doing and if you can admit it, you’re already one step ahead. Acknowledge the feeling, but don’t let it stop your progress. Use your experience, available resources, and most importantly, your judgement to make the best decisions you can. In my experience, one of the most valuable traits we can have is to be adaptable. Because two certainties in life are that things will change and that we can’t know everything.</p><p>All of this reminds me of a great movie quote from Steve Carell’s <em>Dan in Real Life</em>:</p><blockquote>Instead of telling our young people to plan ahead, we should tell them to plan to be surprised.</blockquote>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/i-dont-know-what-im-doing/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/i-dont-know-what-im-doing/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>The Most Important Trait in a Designer (MITIAD)</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>I’ve previously written about the <a href="https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/three-books-that-changed-my-professional-and-personal-perspective">Missing Tile Syndrome</a>, a term coined by author Dennis Prager describing our tendency to fixate on whatever is flawed or missing in a situation. My favorite example he provides is his experience trying to discover the Most Important Trait in a Woman (MITIAW).</p><p>During his dating years, Dennis became obsessed with finding the MITIAW. In his book <em>Happiness Is a Serious Problem</em> he writes, “After one date it would be personality, after another it was physical attractiveness, after another it was intelligence, and after yet another it was good values.” After years of this, his friend Joseph finally pointed out that “the Most Important Trait in a Woman is whatever tonight’s date didn’t have.”</p><p>I’ve found myself thinking about this story a lot lately. Company culture is on everyone’s minds and blogs and “only hiring the right people” is a badge of honor companies wear proudly. And rightly so. The interview process is a lot like dating and we shouldn’t just let anyone into our beds.</p><p>Recently, as a position has gone unfilled for longer than expected, I participated in the same game. I was looking for the Most Important Trait in a Designer and found myself focusing on each person’s missing skills or experience. After one interview it would be strategy, after another it was development experience, after another it was humility, and after yet another it was clear communication. Of course all of these are important and we yearn to find the person who embodies them all.</p><p>So to focus my thoughts and energy, I took a step back. Is there possibly one MITIAD that could apply to all cases? While I’m still not certain what that trait is, I have found a good, albeit subjective measure for it. When I leave the interview, the first words out of my mouth should be, “I <em>can not</em> wait to work with this person.” I should feel a pang of excited urgency, knowing we’ve found the one.</p><p>And if the dating analogy is too much for you (business is business after all), remember many of us spend more waking hours per week with our coworkers than with our spouses. So while searching for the MITIAD can be a distraction, it’s important to articulate what it is we value and what to do when we find it.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/the-most-important-trait-in-a-designer/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/the-most-important-trait-in-a-designer/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Why are designers* so bad at scoping?</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p><em>* I use the term “designers” here for simplicity’s sake, but this applies to developers and other disciplines as well.</em></p><hr><p>Ah, scoping: a topic that hits the nerves of designers and business folk alike. It’s a necessary evil with annoyingly simple reasoning: time is limited and time equals money.</p><p>The two most frustrating (and common) examples of inaccurate scoping are: a.) the designer’s estimate is lower than the actual time it takes to complete the work, and b.) the designer’s estimate is too high to secure the work/satisfy the client. Occasionally designers complete the work in less time than the estimate, but people don’t usually complain about that.</p><p>So why do we suck at scoping? These are the most common reasons I’ve seen over the past few years. The following also assumes (as I do) that people are honest and committed to doing their best.</p><h3>Scoping is not treated as a skill</h3><p>Don’t make the mistake of thinking accurately scoping work is something that everyone can and should do. Scoping is a skill that requires learning and practice just like using Photoshop or writing JavaScript. Designers improve their scoping abilities with more experience.</p><p>Think about turning 15 and getting your driver’s permit. Your mom asks you how long it will take to drive across town. Do you think you could accurately tell her? Or offer the fastest route or the benefits of taking a slower, but safer one? Likely not.</p><p>As a driving adult, you’ve spent years estimating the time it takes to get from point A to point B, discovering less busy streets, and refining the time you leave your home in order to arrive as scheduled. Now you could tell her not only the fastest route, but how the time of day and weather conditions affect timing too. Experience matters.</p><h3>All designers are treated as the same</h3><p>Ask a senior designer and a junior designer for a scope and you’ll get two different answers. And that is perfectly reasonable. Usually, the more experienced the designers, the faster they work. Not only are they more proficient with the tools, they can make decisions quicker and with greater confidence.</p><p>Remember though, your clients are paying for expertise. It shouldn’t cost them more for a junior designer to spend 20 hours doing the work a senior designer could do in ten. In fact, it should be the opposite.</p><h3>There isn’t enough information</h3><p>Sometimes a designer is asked to scope work that isn’t clearly defined. Instead of asking questions or doing preliminary research, he will build extra time into his estimate for uncertainty and potential confusion that will need to be figured out later.</p><p>Asking the right questions before giving an estimate can significantly improve a scope’s accuracy. And most clients will readily deliver the proper information if it will save them time and money.</p><h3>Estimates are treated like promises</h3><p>Experienced or not, an estimate is still an educated guess. Especially with custom work, there are many factors that could affect the timeline of a project. Things change, surprises pop up, technology advances.</p><p>When estimates are treated like promises, designers are pressured to finish the work in the original estimated time, even if the definition or size of the work has changed. This causes them to add in additional time as a security measure they may or may not need.</p><h3>There is confusion about effort vs. calendar time</h3><p>This one seems pretty simple, but happens frequently. Instead of producing an estimate for how many hours it will take to complete the work itself, the designer gives an estimate of when in his schedule he will be able to complete the work.</p><p>An example: A design comp may take the designer only 20 hours to complete, but he has another comp on his plate with higher priority and several meetings this week. He builds that time into his estimate and says the work will take him two weeks. This can easily be solved with better clarity.</p><h3>The designer’s competency is questioned</h3><p>“This will take you seven hours? Well, Philip said he could do it in three. Why will it take you that long?” No one wants to be judged as incapable and sentiments like this are the main reason designers UNDER scope. Estimates will never become more accurate if designers don’t feel comfortable being truthful about them.</p><h3>A few steps to improve scoping</h3><p>Designers can improve scoping accuracy by breaking the work into smaller chunks. The larger and more complex the work, the more difficult to produce an accurate estimate.</p><p>Have junior designers observe senior designers scoping work. What kinds of questions do they ask? How do they deliver their estimates? Later, have those senior designers observe the junior designers and give guidance when needed.</p><p>Compare original estimates to the actual time it took to complete the work. This activity is about analysis and reflection, not placing blame. Use the data to find trends across projects and to help designers hone their scoping skills.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/why-are-designers-so-bad-at-scoping/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/why-are-designers-so-bad-at-scoping/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Things are hard before they are easy</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>Growing up, my family had a meeting every Sunday where we examined our week, celebrated our accomplishments, and reviewed our family mottos. One of these mottos was “Things are hard before they are easy.” I always thought, “well, duh” and moved on. I realized later it wasn’t only an encouragement to continue on a difficult path, but a lesson in humility.</p><p>Before you knew it, you didn’t. I remind myself of this often. Even as adults we can fall victim to the childhood taunt, “You don’t know what [insert thing you should know] is?” And unfortunately this often manifests as doubt and resentment toward our clients or colleagues. Next time, think of it differently. A person’s lack of knowledge or skill is not a burden you must bear; it’s an exciting opportunity to share your experience with them.</p><p>In the end, it’s a decision we make as students and teachers. Resist the urge to give up in the face of difficult challenges and avoid criticizing others for being behind. Instead, empower them to catch up. Because let’s be honest, we’ve all been that kid on the playground that didn’t know what [insert adult word] was.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/things-are-hard-before-they-are-easy/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/things-are-hard-before-they-are-easy/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Start by speaking the same language</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>I’m regularly asked if I believe web designers should practice HTML and CSS. While I do think so (which could be another post or five), it can sometimes be against our favor to jump to this argument right away.</p><p>For designers who do not write CSS, learning how can be difficult and scary. And people saying you don’t know how to do your job can only make it more stressful. I encourage designers to take a small first step in the right direction by learning to speak the developers’ language.</p><p>It can start slowly. Expand your vocabulary to include the words or phrases you’d most likely use when trying to communicate a point. If you visited a foreign country, for example, you’d probably first want to learn how to politely ask for a restroom.</p><p>There are many ways to say the same thing. Find the words that make the most sense to the developer. For a designer trained in typography, the terms “leading” and “tracking” are second nature. However, a CSS developer would be more familiar with “line height” and “letter spacing”. A simple shift in phrasing can make a big difference.</p><p>As you learn, you may find yourself using the terms “margin” or “padding” when instructing a developer to add more negative space. And as your vocabulary grows, so too will the ease of learning to write CSS yourself.</p><p>And remember, while the ability to craft HTML and CSS can certainly make you a stronger designer, clear communication is still most important.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/start-by-speaking-the-same-language/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/start-by-speaking-the-same-language/</guid>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>How I fell in love with designing for the web</title>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>When I was young I wanted to be an artist. This is how all the stories start, right? But really, I did. The romanticism didn’t seem to matter much. All I knew was I loved to tell stories through visuals and to share that with others.</p><p>Skip ahead a few years and I found myself completing a fine arts degree with a sub-emphasis of “Intermedia”, which is just as ambiguous as it sounds. I was immersed in the art community, learning a pretty wide array of skills from life drawing to metal welding. I brushed elbows with some indescribable artistic talent, and trust me, it was humbling.</p><p>At the same time, I’d been teaching myself HTML and CSS and occasionally making a website or two for friends and family. And after graduation I managed to get a job designing and developing professionally. The similarities to the art world were exciting and the differences even more exciting still.</p><h3>It’s not all about me</h3><p>The best thing art school did was expose me to frequent and intense criticism of my work. A thick skin you must have. But I found in the end, it was perfectly fine for audiences to just “not get it” and dare I say, some artists preferred it that way. Work often remained unchanged even after loads of negative feedback. The focus of our work was our artistic statement, sometimes at the expense of the viewer’s experience.</p><p>While self-expression is certainly a part of web design, it is one pillar of many that support a site or application created <em>for the user</em>. I’d never seen so much consideration for the viewers of our work. There are jobs, books, and conferences dedicated to making user experiences better. That’s incredible.</p><h3>Community and connections</h3><p>It wasn’t uncommon for artists to team up for large installations or exhibitions, but it was nothing compared to the collaboration I’ve seen with the web industry. Shipping a quality product requires coordination between several people with varied skill sets. And the different perspectives often push our results farther than we ever could on our own.</p><p>Of course this also extends beyond our immediate teams. Designers and developers take their work and open source it, allowing others to benefit from it and to contribute to it. A beautiful product could be built by strangers scattered all over the world. To me, <em>that’s</em> romantic.</p><h3>Yes, we’re open</h3><p>There’s nothing quite like viewing an art piece in person. But galleries have operating hours and some are thousands of miles away. The web allows people to experience your work at any hour of the day and, especially now, from anywhere they wish. When I was introduced to responsive design, I fell in love all over again. Connect as many people to your content as possible and give them the best possible experience. Accessibility is king.</p><p>And really, two small words sealed the deal for me: view source. And later: inspect element. See how things work, learn from the best, and teach others just by doing.</p><p>There’s got to be a million ways people define art. For me, it’s all about delighting others and connecting people. Designing for the web has allowed me to do that and more, and somehow I get paid to do it.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <link>https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/how-i-fell-in-love-with-designing-for-the-web/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://lynnandtonic.com/thoughts/entries/how-i-fell-in-love-with-designing-for-the-web/</guid>
    </item>

  </channel>
</rss>
